<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and perfect narrative of the several proceedings in the case concerning the Lord Craven, before the Commissioners for Sequestrations and Compositions sitting at Haberdashers-Hall, the Council of State, the Parliament and upon the indictment of perjury, preferred and found against Major Richard Faulconer, the single and material witness against the Lord Craven, concerning the petition to the King of Scots, vvhich as the said Faulconer pretended, was promoted at Breda by the Lord Craven, and wherein, as the said Faulconer deposed, the Parliament of England was stiled by the name of barbarous and inhumane rebels. Shortly after which oath the Lord Cravens estate was voted by Parliament to be confiscate.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1071_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208200</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867172</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867172</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119465</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119465)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 160:E1071[1], 249:E1071[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and perfect narrative of the several proceedings in the case concerning the Lord Craven, before the Commissioners for Sequestrations and Compositions sitting at Haberdashers-Hall, the Council of State, the Parliament and upon the indictment of perjury, preferred and found against Major Richard Faulconer, the single and material witness against the Lord Craven, concerning the petition to the King of Scots, vvhich as the said Faulconer pretended, was promoted at Breda by the Lord Craven, and wherein, as the said Faulconer deposed, the Parliament of England was stiled by the name of barbarous and inhumane rebels. Shortly after which oath the Lord Cravens estate was voted by Parliament to be confiscate.</title>
                  <author>Falconer, Richard, Major.</author>
                  <author>Craven, William Craven, Earl of, 1606-1697.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes Craven's petition to Parliament, the trial of Richard Falconer, and orders issued by Parliament concerning Lord Craven.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Falconer, Richard, --  Major.</term>
               <term>Craven, William Craven, --  Earl of, 1606-1697.</term>
               <term>Confiscations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119465:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A true and perfect NARRATIVE Of the ſeveral proceedings in the CASE CONCERNING The Lord Craven, BEFORE The Commiſſioners for Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Compoſitions ſitting at Haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſhers-Hall, The Council of State, the Parliament: And upon the Indictment of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, Preferred and found againſt Major Richard Faulconer, The <hi>Single</hi> and <hi>Material Witneſs</hi> againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> CONCERNING The Petition to the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> VVhich as the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> pretended, was promoted at <hi>Breda</hi> by the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and wherein, as the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> depoſed, The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> was ſtiled by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHORTLY After which Oath the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate was Voted by Parliament to be Confiſcate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. White.</hi> 1653.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119465:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119465:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the Trial of <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> upon an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment <note place="margin">Term. Trin. xx. Maii. 1653.</note> of Perjury at the Upper Bench Bar in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> in the caſe of the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> It was there publikely pleaded on his behalf: <hi>That there was nothing objected againſt the credit of</hi> Faulconer, <hi>ſo long as there was any other ſtone to turn, though there were endeavors in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>Eſtate came to be ſold, to prevent the Sale thereof: And therefore when all Refuges failed, if they can undermine the credit of this man, then they hope to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Act of Parliament: And that after many tranſactions, and ſettlements grounded upon this mans Information, now muſt he be blaſted by an Artificial Indictment a great while after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe paſſages thus let fall by thoſe who (it ſeems) had not perfect knowledge of the proceedings in Parliament, in the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Caſe, might with ſome of the Auditory, at ſo great a Tryal, paſs as certain truths: It is therefore thought neceſſary to publiſh a <hi>Narrative,</hi> to clear thoſe miſtakes; And yet it muſt be acknowledged that no exception was taken either to the Perſon of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> or to the matter contained in his depoſition againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> before the Votes of confiſcation of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate did paſs; For that it was impoſsible for the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> being neer 800. miles diſtant in <hi>Germany</hi> when thoſe Votes did paſs, to be here upon an hours warning, to make his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to <hi>Faulconers</hi> Depoſition: The Parliament paſsing the Votes of confiſcation the ſame day <hi>Faulconers</hi> Depoſition was reported and read in Parliament: Neither the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> nor any on his behalf being then heard or ſummoned to be heard, nor could any on his behalf procure a Copy of the Depoſitions, before the Votes of confiſcation: It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore held requiſite more particularly to make known the ſeveral tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this huſineſs, and what application hath been made from time to time unto the Parliament, by, and on the behalf of the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> after the confiſcation, and before the Bill for Sale of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate did paſs, that the falſity of this mans Oath might be examined in
<pb facs="tcp:119465:3"/> Parliament, or ſuch other way as the Parliament ſhould pleaſe to direct and appoint; which the Parliament, after many applications to that purpoſe, not thinking fit to give way unto; an Indictment of Perjury was preferred in <hi>London</hi> againſt the ſaid <hi>Faulconer,</hi> the Parliament ſitting, and the Indictment found by the Grand-Jury, and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made acquainted therewith before the Bill for Sale of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate did paſs; and at the Seſsions when the ſaid Indictment was found, <hi>Faulconer</hi> might have been alſo tried, had not the principal witneſs againſt <hi>Faulconer</hi> been committed by Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> after he was ſerved with a <hi>Subpaena</hi> to give Teſtimony againſt <hi>Faulconer,</hi> and kept in Priſon from the firſt day of the Seſsions, till the Seſsions was over, and then ſet at liberty: and before the next Seſsions the Bill for Sale of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate did paſs.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as the ſaid Captain <hi>Biſhop (the Proſecutor of the Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>and a Contractor for a good part of his Eſtate)</hi> appeared more then a witneſs at the Tryal of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> and hath ſince that Verdict endevoured to obſtruct Judgement upon the ſame, againſt ſo notorious and infamous a perſon: It is further thought neceſſary to publiſh the proceedings at the Tryal of the ſaid <hi>Faulconer,</hi> that the World (as well as the Jury) may Judge of the credit of this mans Teſtimony againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> upon which ſo heavy a Judgement as that of Confiſcation was grounded: And with what indifferency the ſaid proceedings at the Tryal are related, it is ſubmitted to the Judgement of the Gentlemen of the ſeveral Inns of Courts, and Practiſers of the Law then preſent in Court, and to all others who heard and took Notes at the ſaid Tryal.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Anth. Craven.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119465:3"/>
            <head>A NARRATIVE Of the Proceedings in the Lord Cravens Caſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ajor <hi>Richard Faulconer</hi> being imployed as a <hi>Spie</hi> into <hi>Holland,</hi> at his return gave Information to Captain <hi>George Biſhop,</hi> then Secretary to the Committee of the Council of State for Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, againſt <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven:</hi> which Information being prepared and reduced into writing by Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> The Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall</hi> were ſent for to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> to adminiſter an Oath <hi>there</hi> unto the ſaid <hi>Faulconer,</hi> who came accordingly: And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tenth of <hi>February</hi> 1650. the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> was ſworn before the ſaid Commiſſioners to the Information following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="testimony">
               <body>
                  <head>Febr. 10. 1650. <hi>The</hi> Information <hi>of Major</hi> Richard Faulconer <hi>of</hi> Weſtbury <hi>in</hi> Hampſhire, <hi>taken before</hi> Samuel Moyer, James Ruſſel, Edward Winſlow, Joſias Barners, <hi>and</hi> Arthur Squib, <hi>Eſquires, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners for Sequeſtrations and Compoſitions, upon Oath:</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Who ſaith,</p>
                  <p>THat about a fortnight before the concluſion of the Treaty at <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Faulconers</hi> Information againſt the Lord <hi>Craven</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Breda,</hi> the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and her two Daughters came to <hi>Breda</hi> to the <hi>Scots</hi> King <hi>Charles,</hi> and went not thence till the King went to <hi>Honſleidike,</hi> a houſe of the Prince of <hi>Oranges.</hi> That during that time, this Informant ſaw the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> divers times in preſence with the ſaid King, and every day with the ſaid King at the Court there, he being there with the Queen
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119465:4"/> of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and her two Daughters, to take <hi>their leave</hi> (as they ſaid) of the King of <hi>Scots</hi> before he went to <hi>Scotland:</hi> That ſeveral Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, about <hi>thirty</hi> in number, made a Petition to the ſaid King, to entertain them to fight for him againſt the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the recovering of his juſt Rights, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtating him in his Throne, and <hi>deputed</hi> this Informant and Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Drury</hi> to preſent the ſaid Petition, who <hi>indeed drew</hi> the ſame. That when the Informant and ſome other Officers came to the Court at <hi>Breda,</hi> intending to preſent the ſaid Petition immediately to the Kings hand, but finding the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> very neer to him, likewiſe the Marqueſs of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> who preſented his brother Sir <hi>Charles Cavendiſh</hi> to kiſs the ſaid Kings hand the evening before the ſaid Kings departure, who this Informant ſaw kiſs the Kings hand accordingly; the Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Cleveland,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Lord <hi>Gerrard,</hi> &amp;c. and a great buſtle of of buſineſs; This Informant, with Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> intreating him to preſent the Petition to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to preſent it to the King of <hi>Scots;</hi> the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> taking the Petition, and reading the ſame Chearfully, ſaid to Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> and this Informant, <hi>There is the Queen of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, deliver it to her, and I will ſpeak for you;</hi> Upon which they applied themſelves to the ſaid Queen, and ſhe preſented the Petition; After which the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> with ſome other Lords went into a withdrawing room, where this Informant and company could not enter; But the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> came forth of the withdrawing Chamber, and told this Informant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <hi>That they ſhould receive an anſwer from the Queen of</hi> Bohemia <hi>to their Petition, and that he had ſpoken to the Queen of</hi> Bohemia <hi>in their behalf,</hi> who afterwards came and told this Informant and company that ſhe had delivered their Petition, and that the King had taken order for it. The <hi>next morning</hi> at three of the Clock the <hi>King departed,</hi> but this Informant and company had their Quarters ſatisfied by the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> according to the ſaid Kings order upon their Petition, and thereby to inable them to follow the ſaid King in the proſecution of theſe Wars againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> which was the effect of their aforeſaid Petition: That this Informant ſaw the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> very often and familiar with the ſaid King, and enter with the ſaid King into the withdrawing Chamber, and ſtaid there, the laſt night the ſaid King was at <hi>Breda,</hi> very late.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Richard Faulconer.<hi>Jur.</hi> 10. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1650. <hi>Coram nobis,</hi> Samuel Moyer, James Ruſſel, Edward Winſlow, Joſias Barners, Arthur Squib.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119465:4"/>
            <p> Colonel <hi>Hugh Reyly</hi> was likewiſe ſworn before the ſaid Commiſſioners at the ſame time, whoſe Information was in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="testimony">
               <body>
                  <head>Febr. 10. 1650.<hi>The</hi> Information <hi>of Colonel</hi> Hugh Reyly, <hi>taken before</hi> Samuel Moyer, James Ruſſel, Edward Winſlow, Joſias Barners, <hi>and</hi> Arthur Squib, <hi>Eſquires, Commiſsioners for compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>Who ſaith,</p>
                  <p>THat during the late Treaty at <hi>Breda,</hi> this Informant did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes <note place="margin">Colonel <hi>Hugh Reyly</hi> his Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Lord <hi>Craven.</hi>
                     </note> ſee the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> with the now King of <hi>Scots</hi> in his Bed-chamber, and alſo walked abroad with him, there being no man more converſant with the King then he. That the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> during the ſaid Treaty, did twice go to <hi>Rotterdam</hi> and <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hagh,</hi> and back again, being imployed, as was commonly <hi>reported</hi> at Court there, by the ſaid King. That the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> had a charge from the King to look to one Mrs. <hi>Barlow,</hi> who (as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and he believes to be true) had a child by the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> born at <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> which he did: and after the King was gone for <hi>Scotland,</hi> the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> took the child from her, for which ſhe went to Law with him, and recovered the child back again, <hi>as is reported.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hugh Reyly.<hi>Jur.</hi> 10. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1650. Samuel Moyer, James Ruſſel, Joſias Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Edward Winſlow, Arthur Squib.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Captain <hi>Thomas Kitchingman</hi> was ten dayes after ſworn before the ſaid Commiſſioners, whoſe Information was as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="testimony">
               <body>
                  <head>Feb. 20. 1650.<hi>The</hi> Information <hi>of Captain</hi> Thomas Kitchingman, <hi>taken upon Oath before the Commiſsioners for compoſitions,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>Who ſaith,</p>
                  <p>THat the ſaid Captain <hi>Thomas Kitchingman</hi> in <hi>April</hi> and <hi>May,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Captain <hi>Kitchingmans</hi> Information againſt the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
                     </note> 1650. Saw the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> ſeveral times with the King of <hi>Scots</hi> at <hi>Breda,</hi> and waiting upon the ſaid King ſeveral times at his Table at <hi>Breda;</hi> This Informant alſo ſaw the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> at the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119465:5"/> ſame time with the King of <hi>Scots</hi> at <hi>Breda,</hi> waiting upon the ſaid King at his Table, and ſaw the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> many times go into the withdrawing rooms after the ſaid King; This Informant alſo ſaw the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> in the Bowling-ally in <hi>Breda</hi> Caſtle with the ſaid King.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Kitchingman.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Jur. coram Commiſsionar.</hi> 
                        <date>Febr. 20. 1650.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Sir <hi>William Craven</hi> having notice that the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> eſtate was in danger of Sequeſtration; and conſidering that himſelf and his children, by <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> daughter to <hi>Fardinando,</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> upon whom a great part of the ſaid eſtate was ſetled, were like to be concerned therein; deſired Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> to go with him to the Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> and to deſire a Copy of the Charge againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and accordingly a Copy of the depoſitions taken againſt the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was demanded by Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth;</hi> To whom Mr. <hi>Moyer</hi> in the name of the reſt of the Commiſſioners, anſwered; That they had not fully conſidered of the Informations againſt the Lord <hi>Craven;</hi> But ſaid that very ſpeedily a Copy of the Charge ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and power ſhould be given to the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> to examine and croſs examine witneſſes; whereupon at that time they departed, being confident that they ſhould never be deprived by thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of that common juſtice of being heard before condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>March 4. 1650.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> having taken into <note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſcruple to Sequeſter the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </note> conſideration the ſaid Informations of <hi>Faulconers, Reylys,</hi> and <hi>Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chingmans,</hi> were not ſatisfied in their judgements that they could Sequeſter the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> thereupon; Wherefore they preſented their doubt in that caſe to the Council of State, which <hi>doubt</hi> or <hi>quere</hi> of theirs, as it is recorded, and recited in an order of the Council of State, was as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="query">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Tueſday</hi> 4. <hi>Martij.</hi> 1650. At the <hi>Council of State</hi> at <hi>White-Hall.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Upon peruſall of the depoſitions touching the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to this Council from the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations, &amp;c. ſitting at <hi>Haberdaſhers-hall;</hi> And of their certificate, wherein they mention that they have given orders for the ſeizing and ſecur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119465:5"/> the ſaid Lords eſtate, but offer it as a doubt, whether the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath made it matter of <hi>Sequeſtration</hi> for any perſon living be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, to hold <hi>correſpondency</hi> with, or repair to the perſon of the now King of <hi>Scots, when</hi> he was <hi>beyond the Seas;</hi> And deſire it may be offered to the Parliament for a Rule, which may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them to proceed to Sequeſtration in that and other caſes of like nature: It is ordered by the Council, that Mr. Atturny Generall do report this matter to the Parliament; and in reſpect the retarding of Sequeſtrations, where perſons may be eſteemed juſtly ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable, tends much to the prejudice and diſadvantage of the State, to deſire that the Parliament will be pleaſed to give ſome directions therein for the expediting of Juſtice in this and the like caſes.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Ex. <hi>Gualter Froſt,</hi> Secr.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>March 6. 1650.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> Atturney Generall, makes his report to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Mr. Atturny Generals Report.</note> according to the directions of the ſaid order, which report of his is entered in the journal book, agreeing <hi>verbatim</hi> with the order of the Council of State of the 4. <hi>March,</hi> and he alſo made a report of the three Informations before mentioned <hi>(viz.) Faulconers, Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes</hi> and <hi>Kitchingmans,</hi> all which were deſtinctly read by the Clerk, and after ſome debate theſe Votes following did paſs againſt the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> unheard, and not having any other Charge againſt him.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="report">
               <body>
                  <head>Die Jovis 6 Martii 1650.</head>
                  <p>REſolved by the Parliament that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> is an offender <note place="margin">The Votes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation.</note> againſt the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> within the Declaration of the 24. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1649. Entituled a Declaration of the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, declaring all Perſons who have ſerved the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and have betrayed their truſt, or have or ſhall adhere to, or aid and aſsiſt <hi>Charles Stewart,</hi> Son to the late King, to be Traytors and Rebels.</p>
                  <p>Reſolved by the Parliament that the Eſtate of the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> be Confiſcated accordingly.</p>
                  <p>Reſolved that the Commiſsioners for Compounding be impowred and required to Seize and Sequeſter all the Eſtate Real and Perſonal of the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and to receive the Rents, Iſſues and Profits thereof to the uſe of the Commonwealth.</p>
                  <p>Reſolved that the Commiſsioners for Compounding be impowred and required to ſeize and Sequeſter into their Poſſeſsion, the real and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Eſtate of all ſuch Perſons as ſhall appear to them to be offenders within the Declaration of the <hi>24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Auguſt</hi> 1649. aforeſaid; and to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119465:6"/> receive and take the Rents, Iſſues and Profits thereof, to the uſe of the Commonwealth.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Scobel Cler. Parliam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Which Declaratory Vote of the Houſe of Commons, of the</hi> 24 <hi>of</hi> Auguſt, 1649. <hi>followeth in theſe words,</hi> viz.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="declaration">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Die Veneris</hi> 24 <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649. Maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> reports from the Council of State a Letter from <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Luke Robinſons</hi> Report.</note> Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> from <hi>London-Derry,</hi> of the 15 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649. and another of the 14 inſtant, with Articles of Agreement between General <hi>Owen Oneal,</hi> and Col. <hi>Richard Coot,</hi> in the behalf of Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> Lord Preſident of Conaught, <hi>Dat.</hi> 22 <hi>May</hi> 1649. which were all this day read.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REſolved upon the queſtion by the Commons aſſembled in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, That this Houſe doth declare that all perſons, whether</hi> Engliſh <hi>or</hi> Scots, <hi>who have been under the</hi> pay <hi>of the Parliament of</hi> England <hi>in the ſervice of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and have revolted and betrayed their Truſt there, and all other perſons who have or ſhall adhere to, or aſsiſt</hi> Charles Stewart, <hi>Son of the late King, or any the forces in</hi> Ireland <hi>againſt the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>are, and be adjudged to be Traitors and Rebels to the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>and all their Eſtates ſhall be confiſcated, and their perſons proceeded againſt as Traytors and Rebels; and that all ſuch Officers as have ſo betrayed their Truſt, be proceeded againſt by a Court-Marſhall</hi> there.</p>
                  <p>Ordered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament that this Declaration be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed, and that it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the Council of State to <hi>communicate</hi> the ſame to the <hi>Lord Lieutenant of Ireland,</hi> and ſuch others <hi>there</hi> as they ſhall think fit, that the ſame may be put in execution.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Hen. Scobel</hi> Cler. Parliam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Sir <hi>William Craven</hi> and Maſter <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> repaired again to the <note place="margin">A ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the charge againſt the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </note> Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> and demanded a Copy of the Informations againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> to the end that he might be heard before he was condemned; for that they underſtood the Commiſſioners had ſeized and ſecured his Eſtate, and did purpoſe to Sequeſter the ſame.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Moyer</hi> returned this anſwer: <hi>That it was not uſual with them to condemn any man unheard, that they had a full purpoſe to have given</hi> 
               <note place="margin">A further An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners at <hi>Haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſhers-Hall.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>liberty to the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>to make his Defence to the Informations gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt him, but now their hands were tyed up, for the Parliament had Voted his Eſtate to be confiſcate: and they were required to Sequeſter</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119465:6"/> 
               <hi>all the Eſtate real and perſonal of the Lord</hi> Cravens, <hi>to the uſe of the Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon Maſter <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> forthwith repaired to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to inform himſelf of the proceedings againſt the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> there: Took a Copy of Maſter Atturny-Generals Report, the Informations aforeſaid, and the Votes of Confiſcation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; and immediatly a Petition was drawn on the behalf of the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> in the name of Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> and <hi>James Picker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Eſq. Commiſſioners intruſted by the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of his Eſtate, which from the 12 of <hi>March</hi> 1650. to the 12 of <hi>June</hi> 1651. they endeavoured by their friends to get de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in Parliament, but could not obtain it, until the ſaid 12 of <hi>June,</hi> that the Houſe took into conſideration the firſt Bill of ſale of Delinquents Eſtates: When the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> name being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to be inſerted into the Bill, it gave a handſome opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to that Member of the Houſe, who had ſo long attended to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>James Chaloner.</hi>
               </note> the ſaid Petition, to get the ſame delivered: which Petition then preſented and read, was in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Supreme Authority of this Nation; the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Sir <hi>William Craven</hi> Knight, and <hi>James Pickering</hi> Eſq. Commiſſioners deputed by the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> for the managing of his Eſtate in his abſence,</head>
                  <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That your Petitioners are informed that by a late Vote of this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe, the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>is declared an Offender within the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The firſt Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſented on the behalf of the Lord <hi>Craven.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>declaration of the</hi> 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>of</hi> Auguſt 1649. <hi>Whereby his Eſtate is made liable to confiſcation, and the Commiſsioners for Compounding are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred and required to ſeize and Sequeſter all the eſtate real and perſonal of the ſaid Lord</hi> Craven; <hi>That the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>being</hi> beyond the Seas <hi>in</hi> Germany, at the time <hi>of the paſsing of</hi> theſe Votes, <hi>knoweth nothing of the Votes againſt him here in</hi> England, <hi>and your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners being deſirous to diſcharge their Truſt, in giving his Lordſhip timely notice of the ſaid proceedings againſt him, Do humbly pray on the behalf of the ſaid Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>that your Petitioners may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſend an Expreſs unto his Lordſhip, to acquaint him with the ſaid Votes; And that this Honorable Houſe would be pleaſed in the mean time, as to the confiſcation of his eſtate, to ſuſpend their former Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>And Your Petitioners ſhall pray, &amp;c.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119465:7"/>
            <p> Upon the reading of this Petition the Houſe thought not fit to make any order to ſuſpend the Votes of Confiſcation, or to give leave to ſend an Expreſs.</p>
            <p>The Parliament afterwards falling again upon the debate of the <note place="margin">The houſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided about the Lord <hi>Craven.</hi>
               </note> firſt Bill of Sale for Delinquents eſtates, it was then propounded that the Houſe would give leave to ſpeak againſt the former Votes of confiſcation of the Lotd <hi>Cravens</hi> eſtate, upon which the Houſe was devided; 24 were for reſuming the debate, and 25 were againſt it; So it was carried by one Vote onely not to reſume the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the ſaid Votes of confiſcation: The Votes which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that day in Parliament were as followeth <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="votes">
               <body>
                  <head>Thurſday 3. <hi>July</hi> 1651.</head>
                  <p>The queſtion being propounded that leave be given to take the Vote touching the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> into conſideration again, it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the negative. <note place="margin">The Votes Summons four months after confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolved by the Parliament, that a Summons do iſſue forth for</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>requiring him to appear parſonally at ſuch time as the Parliament ſhall appoint, to anſwer ſuch matters as ſhall be objected againſt him, on the behalf of the Commonwealth of</hi> England.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolved that the place of his appearance be at the Parliament of the Commonwealth of</hi> England.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolved that the day of his appearance be on the</hi> 3. <hi>of</hi> Septemb. 1651. A draught of the Summons to be ſigned by Mr. Speaker was this day read and agreed unto in theſe words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Authority of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>Theſe are to command and require</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>to make his perſonal appearance before the Parliament of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>upon the third day of</hi> September 1651. <hi>there to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to all ſuch matters as ſhall be objected againſt him on the behalf of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>whereof he is not to fail at his peril, dated at</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>this third day of</hi> July 1651. <hi>Ordered by the Parliament that the Sergeant at Arms attending the Parliament do proclaim this Summons in</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ordered that this Summons be likewiſe printed, and that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant at Arms do cauſe the ſame to be ſet up at the Old Exchange</hi> London, <hi>and other places Convenient for the publication thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Scobel Cler. Parliam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The ſaid Vote of Summons being paſt 4 months after confiſcation, wherof the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> had no notice, yet having got information of ſome former proceedings in the Parliament againſt him and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119465:7"/> his eſtate, when he was far remote in <hi>Germany,</hi> did thereupon ſend a Petition by the forraign Poſt, under the Cover of the Dutch Packet, directed to the Parliament, which was delivered the latter end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1651. by the Dutch Agent, then Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent at <hi>London,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> and by Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi> faithfully preſented to the Parliament before the third of <hi>September</hi> 1651. but the Parliament thought not fit to permit the ſame to be Read; by reaſon there was none preſent who could teſtifie they did ſee the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> ſubſcribe the ſame, and give directions for the delivery thereof; which Petition remains in the hands of Mr. <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> Clerk of the Parliament, and was as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat the Petitioner, notwithſtanding his Care and Endeavour to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The firſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> not permitted to be read.</note> 
                     <hi>avoid giving any Cauſe of offence to the Parliament, hath never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs been ſo unfortunate, as to meet with thoſe who by falſe and Calumnious Informations have practiſed to beget an ill opinion in this honourable Aſſembly of the Petitioner, and thereby as much in them lieth, to work his abſolute ruine, with the falſity of their ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions; The Petitioner doubteth not to make manifeſtly appear, by divers Witneſſes and circumſtances conducing to the clearing of the truth; but in regard the preſent conjuncture of affairs here doth not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to come in Perſon, he doth moſt humbly beſeech the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be ſo favorable unto him, as to give way he may by his friends and Counſel be permitted to anſwer and ſet forth the truth and circumſtances, not doubting but by this means he ſhall be able to clear his innocency, and give ſatisfaction to this Honourable Houſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And your Petitioner ſhall pray, &amp;c. <hi>William Craven.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Craven</hi> haſtens from <hi>Germany</hi> into <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſends <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 1651. A ſecond Petition miſcarried.</note> à duplicate of his former Petition by the hands of Mr. <hi>Peter Wilkin,</hi> a Gentleman formerly of the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and Lord <hi>Fairfax's</hi> Life-guard, a perſon of very much merit and faithfulneſs to the Parliament; who immediatly after he had his diſpatch, fel ſick beyond Sea, and dyed there; the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> being much troubled at his diſaſter, frames a new Petition, and ſends the ſame over into <hi>England</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1651. Subſcribed with his own hand, which <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Gilb. Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Chalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Martin.</hi>
               </note> Petition, with the Duplicates thereof ſo ſubſcribed, as aforeſaid, remained in the hands of ſeveral Members of Parliament, each of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119465:8"/> whom were deſired to take the firſt opportunity that was offered to any of them, to preſent the ſame; Who from <hi>Octob.</hi> 1651. untill 22 of <hi>June,</hi> 1652. though they often endevoured it, and were daily attended therefore by Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> for above ſeven months together, could not prevail to get the Petition read in Parliament; And then the Houſe falling into a debate of an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Act for ſale of Delinquents eſtates, And the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> name being propounded to be inſerted therein, gave a ſeaſonable opportunity to have the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Petition read; which was in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Supream Authority, the Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of</hi> England.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>The humble Petition of</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven.</head>
                  <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat upon the Information of Major <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> who <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A ſecond Petition of the Lord</hi> Cravens.</note> acknowledgeth, That himſelf and another drew the Petition to the King of <hi>Scots</hi> againſt the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> and that the Petitioner promoted the delivery thereof, and upon the information of Captain <hi>Thomas Kitchingman,</hi> and one <hi>Hugh Reyly,</hi> that the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner was at <hi>Breda</hi> with the ſaid King, and upon a Vote of 24 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649. whereby it was declared, that thoſe who had been under pay of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in the ſervice of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and revolted and betrayed their truſt, and all others who did adhere to the Son of the Late King, or any of his Forces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhould be adjudged Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and their Eſtates to be confiſcate, and their perſons to be preceeded againſt as Traitors.</p>
                  <p>Thereupon the 6 of <hi>March</hi> 1650. it was voted in Parliament, that your Petitioner is an Offender within the Declaration aforeſaid, and that his Eſtate be confiſcate, and that the Commiſsioners for compounding be required to ſeize and Sequeſter the ſame, which they have done accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and have ever ſince received the Rents and Profits of all his Lands, and have ſold his Cattle and Goods.</p>
                  <p>The Petitioner ſaith, he is <hi>not guilty</hi> of the matter charged upon him, and humbly deſireth it may be taken into conſideration.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That he went with Conſent of Parliament beyond the Seas before the War broke forth in <hi>England,</hi> and hath been there ever ſince attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Charge.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That he went not to the King of <hi>Scots</hi> into <hi>Holland,</hi> but that the King came to <hi>Breda,</hi> whilſt he was there upon his imployment, where his Reſidence by Command then was.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the material information is upon a ſingle Teſtimony, of one who confeſſeth himſelf the principal contriver of that Treaſon, whereof he accuſeth the Petitioner to be an abettor, and beſides is mainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119465:8"/> and contradicted in divers parts of his Teſtimony, and proves not any <hi>word</hi> or <hi>deed</hi> of the Petitioner, not againſt the Parliament.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the Petitioner during all the Time of theſe late wars and differences in <hi>England,</hi> did never engage, or in the leaſt manner appear againſt the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. That the Perſons that accuſe him were utter ſtrangers to him, and the promotion of their Petition no way concerned him. He humbly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore offers to your Honours conſideration, how unlikely it ſhould be that your Petitioner ſhould hazard himſelf and his Eſtate in <hi>England,</hi> which was known to be conſiderable, in ſo <hi>unneceſſary</hi> and <hi>unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> a buſineſs, and ſo much contrary to all his former Deportments.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore the Petitioner humbly begs the favour of this Honourable Aſſembly, that his Caſe may be conſidered, and that this Honourable Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly would be pleaſed to put his buſineſs into ſuch a way, as that he may be heard by his Counſel, not doubting but thereby this honourable Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly ſhall Receive ſo good an account of your Petitioners candid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, as may fully ſatisfie your Honours.</p>
                  <closer>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>At the ſame time a Member of the houſe delivered a Petition in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> James Chaloner.</note> 
               <hi>the name of Sir</hi> William Craven, <hi>and Sir</hi> Edmund Sawyer, <hi>giving notice of ſome new Information to diſprove</hi> Faulconers <hi>teſtimony, which Petition the ſaid Member moved, that it might be Read, and delivered it to the Clerk accordingly to be Read, immediately after the reading of the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>Petition, but the Parliament thought not fit to permit the reading thereof, which Petition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains with Mr.</hi> Scobel <hi>Clerk of the Parliament, and was in theſe words,</hi> viz.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Supreme Authority of this Nation, the Parliament of the Common-wealth of</hi> England.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> and Sir <hi> Edmund Sawyer </hi>Knights, on the behalf of <hi> William </hi>Lord <hi>Craven,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat they having been a long time truſted in the affairs of the ſaid <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A ſecond Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>not permitted to be Read.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> have for theſe many Moneths attended upon the Parliament, to get a Petition of the ſaid <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> preſented, in which his Humble Deſire is, that he may be heard; That of late it hath come to their knowledge that the information given in by <hi>Faulconer</hi> (the ſingle Witneſs, and againſt the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> in the material parts of his Accuſation) is altogether untrue, and that it will be ſo made appear by ſeveral Witneſſes then upon the place with the ſaid <hi>Faulconer,</hi> and now in Town; and particularly by <hi>Col. Drury,</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119465:9"/> whom the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> mentioned in his accuſation to be deputed with him to deliver the ſaid Petition; who as your Petitioners are informed, can produce the firſt original draught of the ſaid Petition, of the ſaid <hi>Faulconers</hi> own hand writing: whereby it will appear (as your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are likewiſe informed) that there was not the leaſt mention of the Parliament or Commonweath of <hi>England,</hi> nor any ſuch expreſsions as are mentioned in the ſaid <hi>Faulconers</hi> information, which your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners thought themſelves bound in conſcience to acquaint the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment with, that their Juſtice might the more clearly appear in a through examination of this buſineſs, in ſuch way as they in their wiſdom ſhall think fitting.</p>
                  <closer>And your Petitioners ſhall pray, &amp;c.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Afterwards the queſtion being put upon Reading the aforeſaid Petition of the Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>whether he ſhould be put into the Bill of ſale, to have his Eſtate ſold, it was carried only by two voices, that his Eſtate ſhould be ſold, there being</hi> 33. <hi>for the ſale thereof, and</hi> 31. <hi>againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Votes which paſſed that day, are as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="votes">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Tueſday</hi> June 22. 1652.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The houſe this day reſumed the debate upon the Amendments of the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The houſe devided the third time about the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> eſtate.</note> 
                     <hi>additional Act for ſale of Eſtates forfeited to the Commonwealth for Treaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The queſtion being propounded,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven <hi>be put into this Bill for his Lands to be ſold, and the queſtion being put, that this queſtion be now put, it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the affirmative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the main queſtion being put, that</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven <hi>be put into this Bill for his Lands to be ſold, it was Reſolved by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven <hi>be put into the Bill for his Lands to be ſold.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Hen. Scobel</hi> Cler. Parliam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Parliament not thinking fit upon the ſaid Petition of Sir <hi>William Cravens,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edmund Sawyers,</hi> to permit the buſineſs concerning the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> to be put into a way of Examination, and the Bill for ſale being likely to paſs within few dayes, there was a neceſſity put upon the Proſecutors on the behalf of the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> to reſort to the <hi>good Laws</hi> of <hi>England</hi> for remedy; And thereupon, and not before, an Indictment was drawn in order to the conviction of the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> of Perjury, which Indictment was the 12. day of <hi>July</hi> 1652. delivered to the Grand Jury at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119465:9"/> 
               <hi>Guild-Hall London;</hi> The Copy of which Indictment was as <note place="margin">An Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury againſt <hi>Faulconer.</hi>
               </note> followeth.</p>
            <p>Be it remembred, that at the generall Quarter-Seſſions of the <note place="margin">Lond. ſſ.</note> publike peace holden for the City of <hi>London,</hi> at the <hi>Guildhall</hi> of the ſame City, on <hi>Munday</hi> the twelfth day of <hi>July,</hi> In the year of our Lord one thouſand ſix hundred fifty and two, before <hi>John Kendrick</hi> Mayor of the City of <hi>London, Thomas Atkin, Thomas Andrews,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Foot,</hi> Aldermen of the ſame City, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their fellow Juſtices Aſſigned to keep the publike peace in the City aforeſaid: And alſo to hear and determine divers Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Treſpaſſes and other miſdemeanors committed within the ſame City, by the Oaths of <hi>Robert Dawks, John Harvy, William Pitcher, Pelham Moore, George Boddington, Thomas Peirſon, Joſeph Ruthorn, Samuel Coleman, Richard Payn, John Drafgate, Robert Trollaffe, Richard Bartholmew, John Robinſon, Robert Alkington,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Wilmer,</hi> good and lawfull men of the City of <hi>London,</hi> then and there ſworn and charged to Inquire for the Keepers of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of <hi>England</hi> by the Authority of Parliament, and the body of the City aforeſaid, it is preſented that the Bill following is true.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="bill">
               <body>
                  <p>The Jurors for the Keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England</hi> by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <note place="margin">Lond. ſſ.</note> of Parliament upon their Oath do preſent, That <hi>Richard Faulconer</hi> of <hi>Weſtbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Southampton</hi> Gent. Not having the fear of God before his eyes, but moved and ſeduced by the inſtigation of the Devil, and minding and endeavouring to bring the Right Honorable <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> Baron of <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed,</hi> Marſhall in the County of <hi>Berks,</hi> in danger of the loſs of his life, and of the Sequeſtration, confiſcation, forfeiture of all his Lands, Goods, and Chattels within this Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> the tenth day of <hi>February,</hi> In the year of our Lord God one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred and fifty, at the Pariſh of <hi>Mary Stainings,</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Cripplegate London,</hi> before <hi>Samuel Moyer</hi> Eſq; <hi>James Ruſſel</hi> Eſq; <hi>Edward Winſlow</hi> Eſq; <hi>Joſias Barners</hi> Eſq; and <hi>Arthur Squib</hi> Eſq; then being Commiſſioners for compounding with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, and for managing of all and every the eſtates of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents and Popiſh Recuſants; that the fifteenth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the ſaid year of our Lord one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, were, or then after ſhould be under Sequeſtration, did upon the Holy Evangeliſts, corruptly, wilfully, falſly and maliciouſly, of his own proper Act, conſent and Agreement, ſwear, and upon his Corporal Oath before the Commiſſioners aforeſaid on the ſaid tenth day of <hi>February,</hi> in the ſaid year one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, then having power to Adminiſter the ſaid Oath, then and there depoſe concerning the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> in theſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> words following;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119465:10"/> that is to ſay; That about a fortnight before the concluſion of the Treaty at <hi>Breda,</hi> the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and her two Daughters came to <hi>Breda</hi> to the <hi>Scots</hi> King <hi>Charles,</hi> and went not thence till the King went to <hi>Honſleidike,</hi> a houſe of the Prince of <hi>Oranges.</hi> That during that time, this Informant ſaw the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> divers times in preſence with the ſaid King, and every day with the ſaid King at the Court there, he being there with the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and her two Daughters, to take <hi>their leave</hi> (as they ſaid) of the King of <hi>Scots</hi> before he went to <hi>Scotland:</hi> That ſeveral Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, about <hi>thirty</hi> in number, made a Petition to the ſaid King, to entertain them to fight for him againſt the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the recovering of his juſt Rights, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtating him in his Throne, and <hi>deputed</hi> this Informant and Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Drury</hi> to preſent the ſaid Petition, who <hi>indeed drew</hi> the ſame. That when this Informant and ſome other Officers came to the Court at <hi>Breda,</hi> intending to preſent the ſaid Petition immediately to the Kings hand, but finding the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> very neer to him, likewiſe the Marqueſs of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> who preſented his brother Sir <hi>Charles Cavendiſh</hi> to kiſs the ſaid Kings hand the evening before the ſaid Kings departure, who this Informant ſaw kiſs the Kings hand accordingly; the Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Cleveland,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Lord <hi>Gerrard,</hi> &amp;c. and a great buſtle of buſineſs; This Informant, with Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> intreating him to preſent the Petition to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to preſent it to the King of <hi>Scots;</hi> the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> taking the Petition, and reading the ſame Chearfully, ſaid to Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> and this Informant, <hi>There is the Queen of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, deliver it to her, and I will ſpeak for you;</hi> Upon which they applied themſelves to the ſaid Queen, and ſhe preſented the Petition; After which the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> with ſome other Lords went into a withdrawing room, where this Informant and company could not enter; But the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> came forth of the withdrawing Chamber, and told this Informant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <hi>That they ſhould receive an anſwer from the Queen of</hi> Bohemia <hi>to their Petition, and that he had ſpoken to the Queen of</hi> Bohemia <hi>in their behalf,</hi> who afterwards came and told this Informant and company that ſhe had delivered their Petition, and that the King had taken order for it. The <hi>next morning</hi> at three of the Clock the <hi>King departed,</hi> but this Informant and company had their Quarters ſatisfied by the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> according to the ſaid Kings order upon their Petition, and thereby to inable them to follow the ſaid King in the proſecution of thoſe Wars againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> which was the effect of their aforeſaid Petition: That this Informant ſaw the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> very often and familiar with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119465:10"/> the ſaid King, and enter with the ſaid King into the withdrawing Chamber, and ſtaid there, the laſt night the ſaid King was at <hi>Breda,</hi> very late; Which ſaid Oath was the ſaid tenth day of <hi>February</hi> in the year of our Lord one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, at the Pariſh and Ward aforeſaid, reduced in writing, and taken before the ſaid Commiſſioners, then having ſufficient and lawfull power to Adminiſter the ſaid Oath, and to take the teſtimony and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of witneſſes upon their Oaths in ſuch caſes; Whereas in truth neither did the ſeveral Officers, or any Officer make a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſaid King to entertain him or them to fight for him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi> Nor did ſeveral Officers or any Officer make a Petition to the ſaid King to entertain him or them to fight for him againſt the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland.</hi> Nor did ſeveral Officers or any Officer make a Petition to the ſaid King to entertain him or them to fight for him againſt the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> for the recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his juſt rights, or reinſtateing him in his Throne. Nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted he the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> to preſent the ſaid Petition, in the ſaid Oath mentioned; Nor did the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> with the ſaid Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> intreating him to preſent the ſaid Petition to the ſaid Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to preſent it to the ſaid King of <hi>Scots.</hi> Nor did the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> with the ſaid Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> intreat him the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> to preſent the ſaid Petition to the ſaid Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to preſent it to the ſaid King of <hi>Scots.</hi> Nor did the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> take the ſaid Petition, or read the ſame; Nor ſaid unto the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer</hi> and Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> there is the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> deliver it to her, and I will ſpeak for you. Nor did the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> tell the ſaid <hi>Rich. Faulconer</hi> and company, in the ſaid depoſition mentioned, that they ſhould receive an anſwer to their ſaid Petiton, or that he had ſpoken to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in their behalf, As the ſaid <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Faulconer</hi> in and by the ſaid depoſition hath depoſed. And ſo the Jurors aforeſaid, upon their Oath aforeſaid, do ſay, That the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> in manner and form aforeſaid, Corruptly, Wilfully, Falſely and Maliciouſly, of his own proper Act, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Agreement, did commit wilfull, falſe, and corrupt perjury; To the great diſhonor of Almighty God, and to the great damage, loſs and infamy of the ſaid <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and in contempt of the Laws of this Commonwealth; To the evil Example of all others in the like caſe offending, And againſt the publique peace, &amp;c.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Sadler.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119465:11"/>
            <p> This Indictment upon the Teſtimony then produced upon Oath, was accordingly found by the Grand Jury. </p>
            <p>The ſame day that this Indictment was found, Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by Captain <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</hi>
               </note> who had given evidence to the Grand Jury, repaired to <hi>White-Hall</hi> to Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> (having been formerly examined by him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lord <hi>Craven)</hi> and told him, that as he was that morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing going down <hi>Holborn-</hi>Hill, he was ſerved with a Subpaena to appear that day at <hi>Guild-Hall London;</hi> and that he was examined there concerning the Information given by <hi>Faulconer,</hi> againſt the Lord <hi>Craven;</hi> and that after he was ſworn before the Lord Mayor, He gave the ſame evidence to the Grand Jury which he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly given to Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> upon his examination; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſaid Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> took the Writ under ſeal out of his hand, with which he was ſerved to appear, and ſaid to <hi>Drury,</hi> How durſt you be examined againſt the Commonwealth, and not acquaint me firſt therewith? and ſaid further, Mr. Mayor, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (the Lord Mayor) had better have done ſomething elſe, then to have ſuffered that Indictment to be found; and immediatly calls for a Meſſenger, and Commits the ſaid <hi>Drury</hi> to the cuſtody of one <hi>Midleton,</hi> a Meſſenger to the Council of State, who forthwith carried <hi>Drury</hi> away Priſoner into the <hi>Strand,</hi> to the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Midleton,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Drury</hi> was kept by him in ſtrict cuſtody, from <hi>Monday</hi> that the Indictment was found, and the Seſſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, till <hi>Saturday,</hi> that the Seſſions was paſt; by which Reſtraint of <hi>Drury,</hi> who had <hi>Faulconers</hi> own hand-writing to produce againſt himſelf, and being otherwiſe the moſt material witneſs againſt <hi>Faulconer,</hi> there could be no further proſecution upon that Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that Seſſions, and before the next Seſſions the Bill for ſale of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate did paſs. After the preferring and finding of this Indictment, ſeveral bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of publike concernment did interrupt the Parliaments pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent paſſing of the Bill for ſale; So that the Parliament had ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral debates upon the ſaid Act, and the 20 day of <hi>July</hi> the ſaid Bill being committed to a Committee to fill up the full number of 30 perſons, and to preſent their names unto the Houſe, Mr. <hi>Ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> attended with a Petition in the names of Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edmund Sawyer,</hi> and cauſed the ſame to be preſented unto that Committee then ſitting in the Speakers Chamber in the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament Houſe, therein taking notice that the Indictment of Perjury was found; which Petition was as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119465:11"/>
                  <head>To the Honourable the Committee of Parliament, appointed to conſider of the names of ſeveral perſons, to preſent to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, whoſe Eſtates may be forthwith ſold.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edmund Sawyer</hi> Knights, who have been Commiſſioners long intruſted by the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> in the management of his Eſtate.</head>
                  <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat your Petitioners in their Petition preſented to the Parliament</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">A third Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on behalf of the Lord <hi>Craven.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>about a Moneth ſince, and remaining in the Clerks hand, did moſt humbly beſeech them, that they would be pleaſed to permit ſuch Teſtimony to be produced, not onely by witneſs, but by writing under the hand of</hi> Richard Faulconer <hi>(the Single and Material Witneſs againſt the Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>as to the Petition mentioned in</hi> Faulconers <hi>Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) which they hoped would make it clearly appear unto the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; (that the information given by the ſaid</hi> Faulconer) <hi>(upon which the Vote which then paſſed for the Confiſcation of the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>Eſtate is chiefly grounded) is altogether falſe and untrue in all the Material parts of his Examination.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the Parliament not thinking fit to permit the ſaid Petition (preſented as aforeſaid) to be read, the ſaid</hi> Faulconer <hi>is ſince indicted of Perjury, and the Grand Jury have accordingly found the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That a Warrant was accordingly obtained to apprehend the ſaid</hi> Faulconer, <hi>thereby intending to have brought him to his ſpeedy Trial, (all Perjuries being excepted by the Act of Oblivion) but one of the chief Witneſſes againſt the ſaid</hi> Faulconer, <hi>who gave Evidence to the Grand Jury, being ſince reſtrained of his Liberty, was the only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, why in a Legal courſe the Law was not proſecuted againſt the ſaid</hi> Faulconer <hi>this laſt Seſsions at</hi> Newgate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your Petitioners humbly beſeech you, that you would be pleaſed to preſent to the Parliament the conſideration of the whole matter, that this buſineſs may be further and ſpeedily examined in Parliament, or otherwiſe, as they in their wiſdom ſhall think fitting, and that in the mean time the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>may be omitted out of the preſent Bill of ſale.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>And your Petitioners ſhall pray, &amp;c.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Petition was delivered to Aldermam <hi>Allen,</hi> then Chairman to the Committee ſitting in the Speakers Chamber, upon the Bill for ſale; and word was ſent up with the ſaid Petition, that there were ſome attending at the door to avow the ſame, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Petition was read at the Committee, but they thought not fit to take any notice of the information therein given, nor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119465:12"/> the ſame to the Parliament, that their pleaſure might be known thereupon.</p>
            <p>The Parliament again had in debate the ſaid Act, upon a Report thereof made by the Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Grooby,</hi> and paſt many of the Amendments; whereupon it was much preſſed by ſeveral Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that a Petition in the name of Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> and Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Sawyer,</hi> on the behalf of the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> might be read be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Act did paſs; the Houſe at that time thought not fit to hear the ſame, but declared, that before the Bill was put to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, the Petition ſhould be read; and ſhortly after ordered the Bill to be ingroſſed, and to be brought into the Houſe on <hi>Tueſday Auguſt</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tueſday, Auguſt</hi> 3. 1652.</p>
            <p>Accordingly on that day the Speaker tendred the ingroſſed Act to the Houſe, to be put to the queſtion, to paſs as a Law, And the Member of the Houſe in whoſe hands the Petition remained, as he <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Gilbert Pickering.</hi>
               </note> went into the Houſe, was deſired by the Petitioners to preſent the Petition, and to procure them to be called in to avow the ſame, for that they would make good every particular in the ſaid Petition, and more, if need required, then what was thetein contained; which ſaid Member went into the Houſe, and accordingly preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame, which was read by the Clerk, and is remaining ſtill in his cuſtody, and was in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Supream Authority of this Nation, the Parliament of the Common-wealth of</hi> England.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>The humble Petition of Sir</hi> William Craven, <hi>and Sir</hi> Edmund Sawyer <hi>Knights, who have been Commiſſioners long intruſted by the Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>for the managing of his Eſtate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat your Petitioners in their Petition preſented to the Parliament <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A fourth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Lord</hi> Craven.</note> above a Moneth ſince, and remaining in the Clerks hands, did moſt humbly beſeech them that they would be pleaſed to permit ſuch Teſtimony to be produced, not only by Witneſs, but by writing under the hand of <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> the ſingle and material Witneſs againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> as to the Petition mentioned in <hi>Faulconers</hi> depoſition, which they hoped would make it clearly appear unto the Parliament, (that the Information given by the ſaid <hi>Faulconer,</hi> upon which the Vote which then paſſed for confiſcation of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate is chiefly grounded) is altogether falſe and untrue, in all the material parts of his examination.</p>
                  <p>That the Parliament not thinking fit to permit the ſaid Petition ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119465:12"/> preſented, as aforeſaid, to be read, the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> is ſince indicted of Perjury, and the Grand Jury have accordingly found the ſame.</p>
                  <p>That a Warrant was obtained to apprehend the ſaid <hi>Faulconer,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intending to have brought him to his ſpeedy Trial, (all Perjuries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing excepted out of the Act of Oblivion) but one of the material Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes after he gave evidence to the Grand Jury, was the ſame day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited at <hi>White-Hall</hi> to the cuſtody of one <hi>Midldton,</hi> a Meſſenger of the Council of State, and by him kept in ſtrict cuſtody till the Seſsions was ended, which was the only obſtruction why in a Legal courſe the Law was not proſecuted at that time againſt the ſaid <hi>Faulconer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your Petitioners take the boldneſs humbly further to inform the Parliament, that it appears by ſearch in the books kept at <hi>New Priſon</hi> and <hi>Newgate,</hi> That the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer</hi> was committed firſt to <hi>New Priſon,</hi> and then to <hi>Newgate</hi> in <hi>April</hi> Seſsions 1651. upon ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of Felony, where he ſhould have been tried for the fact, but that (as your Petitioners are informed, and hope to prove) there was a ſtop made to the ſaid proceedings, meerly upon an <hi>Affidavit,</hi> That he was in the Parliaments ſervice; beſides it is well known, that the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> was altogether a Stranger to the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and hath ſince his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over, lately confeſſed to Teſtimony of good Credit, that the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> deportment at <hi>Breda</hi> was altogether inoffenſive as to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England,</hi> and that he underſtood nothing of the ſaid buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, more then that a conſideration was deſired to be had of the preſent wants and great neceſsities of the Petitioners.</p>
                  <p>All which your Petitioners humbly ſubmit to the conſideration of the Parliament, beſeeching you to omit the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> out of the Bill of Sale, till this buſineſs be fully examined in Parliament, or by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, or ſuch other way as you in your wiſdom ſhall think fit, and until that other Examinations taken by ſome, deputed by the Council of State, which (as is reported) tend to clear the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the Parliament, as well as thoſe Examinations have been, which ſeem to make againſt the Lord <hi>Craven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>And your Petitioners ſhall pray, &amp;c.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>After the reading of the ſaid Petition, there was very great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate about the ſame, but none of the deſires in the Petition were thought fit to be granted; and thereupon it was put to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>ſhould ſtand in this Bill, to have his Land ſold, and it was carried in the affirmative by three voices, there being</hi> 23 <hi>in the affirmative, and</hi> 20 <hi>in the negative: the Votes which paſſed that day, were in theſe words following,</hi> viz.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="votes">
               <body>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119465:13"/>
                  <head>Tueſday <hi>the third of</hi> Auguſt, 1652.</head>
                  <p>A Bill for ſale of ſeveral Lands and Eſtates forfeited to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth for Treaſon, appointed to be ſold for the uſe of the Navie, was this day read the third time.</p>
                  <p>The humble Petition of Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edmund Sawyer</hi> Knights, who have been Commiſsioners long intruſted by the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> in the management of his Eſtate, was this day read.</p>
                  <p>An intercepted Letter, directed, <hi>A Monſieur Monſieur Carleton a Ezgliſſe de Chapelle Bruzelle,</hi> was this day read.</p>
                  <p>The queſtion being put that <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven</hi> do ſtand in the Bill, it paſſed in the affirmative: Reſolved by the Parliament that <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven</hi> do ſtand in the Bill.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Hen. Scobel</hi> Cler. Parliam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>After the paſſing of theſe Votes, ſeveral Members of the Houſe were acquainted that a great part of the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>Eſtate was entailed, and eſpecially</hi> Comb-Abby, <hi>a Mannor of the Lord</hi> Cravens, <hi>worth</hi> 2500 <hi>li.</hi> per annum, <hi>entailed by</hi> John <hi>Lord</hi> Craven <hi>upon Sir</hi> William Craven, <hi>and the heirs male of his Body, the very next in remainder (at this day) after the now Lord</hi> Craven; <hi>which entail was had in conſideration at the marriage of Sir</hi> William Craven, <hi>with</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>daughter to</hi> Ferdinando <hi>Lord</hi> Fairfax, <hi>the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>then engaging not to deſtroy the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus much being intimated to ſeveral Members of the Houſe, it was anſwered by ſome of them, that ſpecial notice was taken of the entayling of this Eſtate, and that a Clauſe was added to this Act which was not in the former Bill for ſale, which would reſolve the queſtion; A Copy of which Clauſe being procured and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with that which was afterwards in the printed Act, was in theſe words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by this preſent Parliament, and by Authority thereof, That all Reverſions and Remainders expectant upon any Eſtate tail, upon any convetance made by the ſaid Traitor or Traitors, or anyother perſon or perſons, by or under whom they or any of them Claim of any the Manors, Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments of any the Traitor or Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in this Ast, <hi>or in the aforeſaid Act for Sale of ſeveral Lands and Eſtates forfeited to the Commonweath for Treaſon,</hi> named, not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally veſted in the poſſeſsion of ſuch Tenant in Tail by the death of ſuch Traitor or Traitors, before the Five and twentieth day of <hi>March,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty two, which by Fine and Recovery might be Docqued by any of the ſaid Traitor or Traitors, are and ſhall be to all Intents and Purpoſes Forfeited for their ſaid Treaſons; And as well the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119465:13"/> ſaid Traitors and their Heirs and Aſsigns, and all other perſons and their heirs in Reverſion or Remainder upon any ſuch Eſtate, ſhall be for ever barred, as if ſuch Traitor or Traitors had actually levied a Fine, and ſuffered a Recovery for doing thereof, Any <hi>Allowance,</hi> Law, Statute or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 4. 1652.</p>
            <p>The Houſe again reſuming the debate of the ingroſſed Act for Sale; A Proviſo was tendered by Mr. <hi>Strickland</hi> (on the behalf of Sir <hi>William Craven)</hi> who was privy to the agreement of the ſaid marriage of Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided that this Act, nor any thing therein contained, ſhall extend</hi> 
               <note place="margin">A <hi>Proviſo</hi> tendered on the behalf of Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> 
               <hi>to make void any remainder, uſe or reverſion ſetled upon Sir</hi> William Craven <hi>Knight, out of the Eſtate of</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>or</hi> John <hi>Lord</hi> Craven <hi>his brother, whoſe Eſtate is ſince deſcended to</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>at or before this marriage with</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>daughter of</hi> Ferdinando <hi>Lord</hi> Fairfax, <hi>deceaſed; any thing in this Act contained to the contrary thereof, in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Proviſo after the reading thereof, and ſome debate thereupon, was rejected; And the Bill for Sale of the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> Eſtate immediatly thereupon paſſed, as a Law.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Craven</hi> ſhortly after having notice that the Bill was <note place="margin">The Lord <hi>Craven</hi> reſolvs of a further addreſs to the Parliament.</note> paſt for Sale of his Eſtate; and that the Surveyors were ſent down into the Country to Survey the ſame, in order to a preſent Sale; and being deſirous to preſerve the ſame (though confiſcated, yet) from being cantanized into ſeveral hands; was deſirous again humbly to Petition the Parliament, and thereupon retired out of <hi>Holland</hi> to <hi>Bruſſels</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and from thence did write a Letter to Mr. Speaker, all of his own hand writing, and therein incloſed a Petition, ſubſcribed alſo with his own hand, ſubmitting to ſuch ſumme of money as the Parliament ſhould pleaſe to impoſe upon him; and alſo ſent Duplicates of that Petition to his friends, to be preſented to the Parliament, in caſe the Speakers Letter and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the Parliament ſhould miſcarry, and withall did ſignifie to his friends his readineſs to come over in perſon, and (though inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of the charge againſt him) Yet was reſolved to ſubmit unto, and ſatisfie ſuch ſumme of money as the Parliament ſhould impoſe upon him; hoping they would rather chooſe that way, then utterly to ruine him in his Eſtate and fortunes, by permitting his Houſes to be pulled down, his Woods to be felled, and his Lands to be ſold to ſtrangers; Hoping alſo, that it would be conſidered he was a perſon innocent, as to blood, plunder, or violence in the late unnaturall Wars in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> having gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Seas by leave of Parliament, and reſided there ever ſince, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119465:14"/> now, being neer twelve years together, attending his charge there, under the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Which Letter and Petition from the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> delivered by Mr. Speaker to the Clerk to be read, were as followeth.</head>
                  <head type="sub">To the Honorable <hi>William Lenthall</hi>Eſq; Speaker of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ALthough I am altogether a ſtranger to your Honour, yet as my misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A Letter from the Lord</hi> Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>to Mr. Speaker.</hi>
                     </note> is at preſent, I do not know how to avoyd giving you the trouble of addreſsing this incloſed ſupplication to you, for the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England;</hi> the which I ſhall humbly beſeech you, out of your accuſtomed civility to all perſons that have recourſe to you in this kinde, to preſent it with that advantage, that it may be permitted to be Read, and taken into conſideration of that Honourable Houſe, having been far other in my comportment, then what by misfortune I have been calumniated to have been; ſo that I hope their grace and favour will be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded according to this my reaſonable requeſt; the which no perſon ſhall acknowledge with more reſpect towards them, nor your favour herein with greater value of your generoſity and goodneſs, then what he ſhall do, that deſires to have cauſe to be</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your moſt affectionate and obliged Servant,</hi> William Craven.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Septemb. 3. 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Supreme Authority of this Nation, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat whereas it hath been your Petitioners ſore affliction to fall into</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">A third Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition from the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> to the Parliament.</note> 
                     <hi>the diſpleaſure of this honourable Parliament, and to remain under your moſt heavy ſentence, yet conſidering that the ſeverity thereof was ſuch, (reaching both Life and Eſtate) as might juſtly deterr him from adventuring in perſon into</hi> England, <hi>and conſidering that it hath not been the manner of this honourable Houſe of Parliament, to execute their judgements to the ruine of families, where there hath been any hopes of rendring them ſerviceable to the Commonwealth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In theſe reſpects he is encouraged in moſt humble manner to intreate your wonted Clemency, in the remiſsion of your heavy Sentence againſt his Life and Perſon, and that paying a reaſonable ſumme of money, he may be reſtored to his Eſtate, whereby both he, and thoſe who have</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119465:14"/> 
                     <hi>juſt Title in Law to it after his death, (being preſerved from Ruine) will be obliged to be your Honours in all Reſpective Demeanor and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>And your Petitioner ſhall pray, &amp;c. <signed>William Craven.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But the houſe was devided whether to permit the Petition to be read; Yet afterwards reſolved to read the ſame; Whereupon the Petition was read; And his Excellency the Lord Generall much preſſed the houſe, that notwithſtanding their reſolution to ſell the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate, yet that they would rather impoſe a ſumme of money upon the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> for that he judged it to be more Honorable, then to expoſe his Eſtate to Sale, and intimated a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ſumme indeed; Beſides the 30000. li. which had been already received out of his Rents and perſonal Eſtate, and by the dammage done to his Woods.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>William Craven,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edmund Sawyer</hi> did attend at the door at that time, expecting to be called in, to give aſſurance to the Parliament, that the ſumme of money which they ſhould think fit to impoſe upon the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> ſhould be ſpeedily raiſed.</p>
            <p>As the Houſe was in debate of this buſineſs, the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador was admitted to have Audience to take his leave, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, and the Ambaſſador gone, it was moved to reſume the debate again; But the contrary was preſſed by others; and the Speaker was required to propound the Queſtion, whether the Houſe ſhould any further reſume the debate of that buſineſs; The Houſe was thereupon devided; And it was carried in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative <note place="margin">The Houſe devided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain about the Lord <hi>Craven.</hi>
               </note> by four Voices, there being thirty four againſt taking any further conſideration of his Petition, and thirty for reſuming the debate thereof; The Votes which paſſed that day, were as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>Friday 29. <hi>Octob.</hi> 1652. A Petition of the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> being preſented,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REſolved by the Parliament, that his Petition be now Read; And the Petition was now Read accordingly, and was Entituled, The Humble Petition of</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven.</p>
                  <p>The Queſtion being put,</p>
                  <p>That the Houſe do proceed further in the debate upon the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the Lord <hi>Craven;</hi> it paſſed in the Negative.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Scobel Cler. Parliam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119465:15"/>
            <p> After this Vote there was no further application made to the Parliament on the behalf of the Lord <hi>Craven;</hi> For that Surveyors were gone to the ſeveral Counties to Survey his eſtate; and ſome Surveys were actually returned, and dayes appointed for Sale.</p>
            <p>And the Members of the Houſe ſtept in with the firſt to buy the flower of his Eſtate, to the value of five or ſix thouſand pound <hi>per annum,</hi> as appears by the Contracts made at <hi>Drury-Houſe</hi> in their own names, and in the names of others intruſted for the uſe of Members.</p>
            <p>That ſtately Houſe of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> at <hi>Cauſam</hi> neer <hi>Reading,</hi> in excellent repair, was bought by ſome perſons, who for greedy lucre and gain, utterly defaced the ſame, pulled down the Wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot, Stayr-Caſes, Lead, Iron, and all the the materials about the houſe, which coſt building 20000. li. they giving the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth little above 1500. li. in moneys (the price of deben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters therein alſo inccluded.)</p>
            <p>It being now Term time when the houſe was the laſt time devid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and there being no hopes to have his caſe further heard, it was thought neceſſary and convenient how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to expedite the Triall upon the Indictment of perjury againſt <hi>Faulconer;</hi> Whereupon courſe was taken to remove the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by a <hi>Certiorari</hi> into the upper Bench, to the end the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> might be Out-Lawed for Perjury; The Record being accordingly removed, a <hi>Capias</hi> in order to an Out-lawry was taken out againſt the ſaid <hi>Faulconer,</hi> who for ſeveral Seſſions before had refuſed to appear: At laſt the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> was taken upon the ſaid <hi>Capias,</hi> and carried to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where he lay for ſome time, and would not appear nor plead to the Indictment; Whereupon the proſecutors for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth were inforced to move the Court for a <hi>Habeas Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> to bring him to the Bar, that he might be enjoyned to plead, and accordingly the Court required him to plead; Whereupon he pleaded <hi>Not guilty</hi> to the Indictment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hillary Term.</hi> 1652.</p>
            <p>In Hillary Term following a day was appointed for Trial upon the Indictment, at <hi>Guild-Hall London,</hi> before the Lord chief Juſtice <hi>Rolls,</hi> where the ſaid Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>Faulconer</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their Counſel and Witneſſes; And Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in behalf of the Commonwealth with Counſel and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and had given in the Record to have the Jury called, but it ſo fell out, that a perſon of integrity then in Court, who had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119465:15"/> certain knowledge when and where the ſaid Oath was taken; gave Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> notice, that the Oath given to <hi>Faulconer,</hi> was adminiſtred unto him at <hi>White-Hall</hi> in <hi>Middleſex,</hi> and not at <hi>Haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſhers-Hall</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and therefore the place being miſlaid in the Indictment, a <hi>London</hi> Jury could not find a fact done in <hi>Middleſex:</hi> Whereupon Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> immediately withdrew the Record for that time, and gave a ſtop to the Triall.</p>
            <p>No time was miſpent to recover this miſtake: For within two dayes a new Indictment was drawn, and preferred to the Grand Jury in <hi>Middleſex,</hi> (Sir <hi>Henry Blunt</hi> being Foreman) where the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment was found: and was as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="indictment">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Hillary Term</hi> 1652.</head>
                  <p>Before this time, that is to ſay, upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> next after the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <note place="margin">Middleſex.</note> of the <hi>Purification</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> this ſame Term, before the Keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England</hi> by authority of Parliament, in the Upper-Bench at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> by the Oaths of twelve honeſt and lawful men, it is preſented, That <hi>Richard Faulconer</hi> late of <hi>Weſtbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Southampton</hi> Gent. Not having the fear of God before his eyes, but moved and ſeduced by the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Devil, and minding and endevouring to bring the Right Honorable <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> Baron of <hi>Hampſteed,</hi> Marſhall in the County of <hi>Berks,</hi> in danger of the loſs of his life, and of the Sequeſtration, confiſcation, and forfeiture of all his Goods, and Chattels, Lands and Tenements within this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England,</hi> the tenth day of <hi>February,</hi> In the year of our Lord God one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Martins</hi> in the Fields, in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> before <hi>Samuel Moyer</hi> Eſquire, <hi>James Ruſſel</hi> Eſquire, <hi>Edward Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlow</hi> Eſquire, <hi>Joſias Barners</hi> Eſquire, and <hi>Arthur Squib</hi> Eſquire, then being Commiſſioners for compounding with Delinquents, and for managing of all and every the eſtates of Delinquents and Popiſh Recuſants; that the fifteenth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the ſaid year of our Lord God one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, were, or then after ſhould be under Sequeſtration, did upon the Holy Evangeliſts, corruptly, wilfully, falſly and maliciouſly, of his own proper Act, conſent and Agreement, ſwear, and upon his Corporal Oath before the Commiſſioners aforeſaid, on the ſaid tenth day of <hi>February,</hi> in the ſaid year one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, then having ſufficient and lawfull power to Adminiſter the ſaid Oath, and to take the teſtimony and depoſitions of witneſſes upon their Oaths in ſuch caſes, then and there depoſed; That ſeveral Officers,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119465:16"/> about <hi>thirty</hi> in number, made a Petition to the <hi>Scots</hi> King <hi>Charles,</hi> to entertain them to ſight for him againſt the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the recovering of his juſt Rights, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtating him in his Throne. And did alſo then and there, corruptly, willfully, falſly, and maliciouſly, before the ſaid Commiſſioners, ſwear, that the ſaid Officers deputed him, the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> to preſent the ſaid Petition, who (as the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> then and there, corruptly, willfully, falſly, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly, before the ſaid Commiſſioners did ſwear, indeed drew the ſame; And did alſo, then and there, corruptly, willfully, falſly and maliciouſly before the ſaid Commiſſioners, ſwear, that he the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> with Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> applyed themſelves to the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> (meaning the aforeſaid <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven)</hi> intreating him to preſent the ſaid Petition to the Queen of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> to preſent it to the King of <hi>Scots:</hi> And did alſo then and there, corruptly, wilfully, falſly and maliciouſly before the ſaid Commiſſioners, ſwear, that the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> taking the ſaid Petition, and reading the ſame cheerfully, ſaid unto Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> and him the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> There <hi>Is the Queen of</hi> Bohemia, <hi>deliver it to her, and I will ſpeak for you:</hi> And that the ſaid Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> did preſent the ſaid Petition; and did alſo then and there, corruptly, wilfully, falſely and maliciouſly, before the the ſaid Commiſſioners, ſwear, that the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> after told him the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> and company, that they ſhould receive an anſwer from the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to their Petition, and that he (meaning the ſaid <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven)</hi> had ſpoken to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in their behalf: Whereas in truth, neither did ſeveral Officers, or any Officer make a Petition to the ſaid King to entertain him or them to fight for him againſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England.</hi> Nor did ſeveral Officers or any Officer make a Petition to the ſaid King to entertain him or them to fight for him againſt the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland.</hi> Nor did ſeveral Officers or any Officer make a Petition to the ſaid King to entertain him or them to fight for him againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the recovering of his juſt rights, or reinſtating him in his Throne. And whereas in truth, the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by the ſaid Officers to preſent the ſaid Petition, in the ſaid Oath mentioned; and whereas in truth, he the ſaid <hi>Richard Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner,</hi> with Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> did not apply themſelves to the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> intreating him to preſent the ſaid Petition to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to preſent it to the ſaid King of <hi>Scots.</hi> Nor
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119465:16"/> did he the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> with the ſaid Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat him the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> to preſent the ſaid Petition to the ſaid Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to preſent it to the ſaid King of <hi>Scots.</hi> And whereas in truth, the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> did not take the ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor read the ſame; Nor ſay unto the ſaid Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> and him the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> there is the Queen of <hi>Bohemia, deliver it to her, and I will ſpeak for you:</hi> And whereas in truth the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> did not tell him the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> and company, in the ſaid depoſition mentioned, that they ſhould receive an anſwer from the ſaid Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to the ſaid Petition, nor that he the ſaid Lord <hi>Craven</hi> had ſpoken to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in their behalf, As the ſaid <hi>Richard Faucloner,</hi> in and by the ſaid depoſition hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. And ſo the Jurors aforeſaid, upon their Oaths aforeſaid, do ſay, That the ſaid <hi>Richard Faulconer,</hi> in manner and form afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, Corruptly, Wilfully, Falſly and Maliciouſly, of his own proper Act, Conſent and Agreement, did commit wilfull, falſe, and corrupt perjury; To the great diſhonor of Almighty God, and to the great dammage, loſs and infamy of the ſaid <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and in contempt of the Laws of this Commonwealth; To the evil Example of all others in the like caſe offending, And againſt the publique peace, &amp;c.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The reaſon wherefore this Indictment did not recite the Oath <hi>in haec verbae,</hi> as in the former Indictment, but aſſigned the Perjury in the material parts of the Oath; was by reaſon it came lately to knowledge, that the original Oath could not be found, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Oath was to be proved by the Entries in the book of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> and by the Teſtimony of the Perſons who adminiſtred the Oath.</p>
            <p>The next day after the Indictment was found, the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> moved the Court for a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> to bring <hi>Faulconer</hi> to the Bar to plead to the Indictment, who being brought into Court, deſired time to plead till the next Term. Whereupon the Court made this order,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the ſaid</hi> Faulconer, <hi>having now in Court appeared unto the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, ſhould have time to plead unto the ſame, untill the beginning of the next Term, ſo that the iſſue thereupon may be tried at the Bar in open Court the ſame Term.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="court_order">
               <body>
                  <head>Term <hi>Paſch.</hi> 1652.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Faulconer</hi> having all this vacation neglected to appear, or plead to the Indictment, the Proſecutors for the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced again to move for another <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> to bring <hi>Faulconer</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119465:17"/> to the Bar, to appear, or plead to the Indictment; who appearing, deſired longer time to attend his Counſel, which the Court grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed accordingly, and the ordinary Rules of Court were given unto him for the peremptory dayes of pleading, or Judgement to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt him; and the very laſt day, when the laſt Rule was out, and not before, he pleaded <hi>Not guilty.</hi> And the Court order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the iſſue upon the Indictment of Perjury againſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, be tryed at the Bar upon <hi>Friday</hi> in the morrow of the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion</hi> of our Lord, and that the Sheriffe of <hi>Middleſex</hi> do attend <hi>Andrew Broughton</hi> Eſq; with the Book of Freeholders, forthwith, ſo that an indifferent Jury may be returned between the ſaid Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the ſaid Defendant, to try the iſſue aforeſaid, by conſent of the parties on both ſides.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Broughton</hi> accordingly appointed the Sheriffe to attend him the next day in the afternoon, with the Book of Freeholders, who accordingly named the Jury, and notice was given by the Sheriffe, requiring them to appear at the day of Tryal.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119465:17"/>
            <head>The Trial of Richard Faulconer, <hi>Friday, May</hi> 20. 1653.</head>
            <p>THe Jury appearing according to Summons, and <hi>Faulconer</hi> being brought in Cuſtody, the Court proceeded to Triall, and ordered the Indictment to be read; which being afterwards open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Mr. <hi>Boynton,</hi> the Evidence was managed by Mr. <hi>Maynard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> Mr. <hi>Twiſden,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilde,</hi> Mr. <hi>Philips,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baldwin,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Drury;</hi> who were of Counſel for the Commonwealth againſt the ſaid <hi>Faulconer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before the Counſel for the Commonwealth proceeded to produce any Witneſſes, they offered unto the Court and the Jury ſomething in general concerning the Indictment. That the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment was for the crime of Perjury, willfully and corruptly committed; That <hi>Faulconer</hi> makes an Oath, that there was a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion delivered, in which there was a very ſharp reflexion (as he ſwears) upon the Parliament, by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Rebels;</hi> he ſwears he was deputed to deliver it, being drawn by himſelf and <hi>Drury,</hi> &amp; ſubſcribed by 30 Officers; that in order to the delivery thereof, they did require the aſſiſtance of the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> that he promiſed to ſpeak for them, and brought them an anſwer; but they hoped to prove unto the Jury, that this Oath which <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner</hi> did take, was very falſe, that it was by deſign, a deſign for money, that the conſequence of it was very notorious, the ruine of that Gentleman, of his Eſtate, Fame and Fortune; That Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes will be produced to prove, what in truth the Petition was; there was a Petition delivered, but not a Petition to this effect at all, and <hi>Faulconer</hi> knew the contrary; we ſhall produce what it was, and that under his own hand, whereby it will appear that there was no ſuch matter in it, as he hath depoſed; the Witneſſes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will beſt ſpeak the Particulars.</p>
            <p>For the opening of ſome things concerning this Oath of <hi>Faulco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> it is to be obſerved, he took this Oath before the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall</hi> at <hi>White-Hal,</hi> and was there reduced into Writing, and a Tranſcript was made of the Original: which Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript was ſent to the Council of State, and they ordered the ſame to be reported to the Parliament, and being reported there, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the Journal Book, and there remains a Record in Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119465:18"/>
            <p> The firſt thing therefore inſiſted upon by the Counſel for the Commonwealth; was the proving of a true Copy of <hi>Faulco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Proofs of <hi>Faulconers</hi> depoſition by a Copy thereof te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall.</hi>
               </note> depoſition, in reſpect the Original was loſt, or rather imbezel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Faulconer,</hi> to prove the ſame.</p>
            <p>A Copy thereof was produced in Court, which agreed <hi>verbatim</hi> with that depoſition of his, which was filed upon Record at <hi>Haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſhers-Hall;</hi> (the Proper Court where it ought to remain) and though that upon the File was but a Copy, yet it was filed as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of that Depoſition he was ſworn unto by them; but this was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Faulconers depoſition</hi> tranſmitted to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of State.</note> oppoſed by the Counſel for <hi>Faulconer,</hi> as not ſufficient proof; and thereupon a Copy of an order of the Council of State of <hi>March</hi> 6. 1650. was produced unto the Court, whereby it did appear, that the Depoſitions againſt the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> had been tranſmitted to the Council of State, by the Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Atorney General pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced as a witneſs.</note> and it appeared further by the ſaid Order, that Mr. Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral was appointed by the Council of State, to report theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to the Parliament, ſo tranſmitted to that Council by the Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall;</hi> and the Attorney General being ſworn in Court, did declare that he reported no other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to the Parliament, then what he received from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Faulconers</hi> depoſition reported to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Mr. Atorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</note> of State; and that the Depoſitions produced to him in Court, (whereof the ſaid <hi>Faulconers</hi> was one) was endorſed with the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing of the Lord <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> then Lord Preſident of the Council of State; and that the Votes of confiſcation of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate did paſs upon the report of the ſaid Depoſitions, which he preſented to the Parliament from the Council of State.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Fermin,</hi> Chief Clark to Mr. <hi>Scobel,</hi> Clark of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Faulconers</hi> depoſition entred in the Journal of Parliament.</note> did depoſe in Court, that the very ſame Depoſitions ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Court to Mr. Attorney General, endorſed with the Lord <hi>Bradſhaws</hi> hand-writing, were entered in the Journal Book, as read in Parliament that day when Mr. Attorney General did make his report unto the Parliament, which he knew the better to be true, for that he received the ſame from the hands of Mr. <hi>Scobel,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Darnel,</hi> the Clark aſſiſtant in Parliament, the ſame day they were read in Parliament, to be entred in the Journal Book; and <note place="margin">Votes of confiſcation entred with <hi>Faulconers</hi> depoſition.</note> that he did enter the ſame accordingly with the Votes of confiſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which paſſed upon the reading of thoſe Depoſitions; and afterwards he and Mr. <hi>Darnel</hi> did examine the ſaid Depoſitions, whereof the ſaid <hi>Faulconers</hi> was one, after the ſame were ſo entred into the Journal Book. <note place="margin">The Journal Book of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in Court to prove <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coners</hi> depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And for the further ſatisfaction of the Court, he produced the Journal of Parliament, wherein the ſaid Depoſitions (and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly that of <hi>Faulconers)</hi> were entred, which were read in Court, out of the Journal, whereby it did appear that the Depoſitions of the ſaid <hi>Faulconer, Kitchingman</hi> and <hi>Reyly,</hi> were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the ſaid Journal, and did agree <hi>verbatim</hi> with the Copy
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119465:18"/> of <hi>Faulconers,</hi> and their Depoſitions remaining at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> and with the Copy reported by Mr. Attorney General from the Council of State to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Winſlow,</hi> one of the Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Winſlow</hi> produced to prove <hi>Faulco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> being one before whom the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> was ſworn, did teſtifie upon Oath in Court, that the depoſition of <hi>Faulconer</hi> produced unto him, and whereupon there was an endorſement of the Lord <hi>Bradſhaws</hi> hand-writing; Was, as he did believe, a true Copy of that depoſition to which the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> was ſworn at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> for that he findeth his <hi>own hand</hi> ſubſcribed thereunto; <hi>(as exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him to be a true Copy)</hi> and ſaid it was uſual with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> when they take Examinations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any perſon of quality, to appoint one of themſelves to go from the Table to examine the Copy by the Original: But whether when he ſubſcribed his name unto the Copy produced unto him, he did examine the ſame by the original depoſition before it was ſent for away by the Council of State, or afterwards, or by the tranſcript remaining upon the File as a Record at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> he could not poſitively remember; But conceives that the Copy to which his hand is ſubſcribed, as examined by him, to be a true Copy, was taken when they had the Original in Cuſtody; but cannot certainly ſay it.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Barners,</hi> Another of the Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Barners</hi> produced to prove <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coners</hi> depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> before whom alſo the ſaid Oath was taken, did teſtifie upon Oath, that to the beſt of his remembrance, the particulars mentioned in <hi>Faulconers</hi> depoſition, then read in Court, were the ſame to which the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> was ſworn unto by himſelf and the reſt of the Commiſſioners, though he could not remember every Syllable and Letter.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Winſlow,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Barners</hi> were again produced to declare <note place="margin">The clauſe of <hi>[Barbarous and Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Rebells &amp;c.]</hi> proved by Mr. <hi>Winſlow</hi> and Mr. <hi>Barners.</hi>
               </note> what they did remember concerning this clauſe in the depoſition of the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> (viz.) <hi>That ſeveral officers, about thirty in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, made a Petition to the King of</hi> Scots, <hi>to entertain them to fight for him againſt the Commonwealth of England, by the name of</hi> Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells, <hi>either in</hi> England <hi>or</hi> Scotland, &amp;c. and thereupon Mr. <hi>Winſlow</hi> did declare unto the Court, that he did well remember that clauſe in <hi>Faulconers</hi> depoſition when he was ſworn thereunto, but whether the number of Officers were thirty or no, he could not tell, but a certain number of Officers were named.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Barners</hi> did declare the like, but whether the word <hi>Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Barners.</hi>
               </note> was in, he could not poſitively ſay; But was certain that <hi>Barbarous Rebells</hi> was contained in that clauſe; and that when <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner</hi> was ſworn unto the ſame, it was firſt read unto him, and amended in ſeveral places, and then he ſwore it to be true: And Mr. <hi>Barners</hi> ſaid, that he did remember his depoſition the better, for that himſelf and the reſt of the Commiſſioners had ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119465:19"/> upon it at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> whether they ſhould thereupon Seize, Sequeſter or ſecure the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> eſtate.</p>
            <p>Having thus traced this Oath of <hi>Faulconers,</hi> which was taken at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and brought to <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> afterwards brought from <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall</hi> back again to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and from <hi>White-Hall</hi> to the Parliament, and there entred in the Journal book, as the grounds upon which the Vores of confiſcation did paſs, and having withall proved that particular clauſe of <hi>Barbarous and Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Rebells,</hi> &amp;c. the Counſel for the Commonwealth concluded as to that point, and left it to the Jury to Judge, and to <hi>Faulconer</hi> to produce the Original, which he hath got into his cuſtody, if he can find any variance in it from the depoſition recited in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment.</p>
            <p>And to prove that <hi>Faulconer</hi> had got the Original Oath into his cuſtody; Mr. <hi>Knight</hi> a witneſs was produced, who did teſtifie upon Oath, that being in the company of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> he did ſhew him a writing written with Captain <hi>Biſhops</hi> own hand, (ſo far as he could judge one mans hand to be like another) and that <hi>Faulconers</hi> name was ſubſcribed thereunto, and that <hi>Faulconer</hi> told him the ſaid <hi>Knight,</hi> that that writing was the Original Depoſition he was ſworn unto, againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and which he kept on purpoſe to keep Mr. <hi>Biſhop</hi> in aw <hi>(Faulconer</hi> being then in neceſſity and want) and that the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> further ſaid unto him, the ſaid <hi>Knight,</hi> that he had received 20. li. for the buſineſs of the Lord <hi>Cravens,</hi> and was to have more, but ſaid he deſerved 2000. li. for what he had done.</p>
            <p>In the next place the Counſel for the Commonwealth did apply themſelves to prove the falſity of the Oath <hi>(viz.)</hi> That there was no ſuch thing in the Petition mentioned by <hi>Faulconer</hi> in his Depoſition <hi>[As that thirty officers did Petition to be entertained to fight for the King of</hi> Scots <hi>againſt the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>by the name of</hi> Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells, &amp;c.] and being to prove a <hi>Negative,</hi> they applied their proof to a certain time and place, which <hi>Faulconer</hi> in his own Depoſition did prove for them, for he ſwears that the Petition was delivered the Evening before the King of <hi>Scots</hi> went from <hi>Breda,</hi> and that the ſaid King went away the next morning at three a clock; He ſwears further, that he and <hi>Drury</hi> drew the Petition, and were deputed to deliver the ſame, accordingly they applied their evidence.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119465:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Proofs, as to the falſity of</hi> Faulconers <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAſter <hi>Horſnell</hi> being produced, did teſtifie; That the night before the King of <hi>Scots</hi> went from <hi>Breda,</hi> Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Horſneſs</hi> Teſtimony againſt <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner,</hi> as to the Petition.</note> Captain <hi>Briſco,</hi> and divers others were with a little ſhort Petition to remember the King of a former Petition which they had delivered, that ſome courſe might be taken that their arrears which they owed in the Town might be paid, that their Landlords where they lodged might not ſuffer, for they were not able themſelves to pay them; that he went along with them to the great window juſt over the moat, and there he the ſaid <hi>Horſnel</hi> did ſet his hand unto the ſame, and that he was in the Chamber when <hi>Drury</hi> and <hi>Briſco</hi> came in to deliver the Petition, in which there was not a word that concerned any thing, but onely the relief of their preſent neceſſities; being asked by the Court, if there were not a mention of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells;</hi> he anſwered, not any thing of that nature was in it; He further ſaid, that this Petition had reference to a former Petition he was not acquainted withall, nor was his hand ſet to the former Petition.</p>
               <p>Captain <hi>Briſco</hi> being produced, did teſtifie, that there were <note place="margin">Captain <hi>Briſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coes</hi> Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt <hi>Faulconer,</hi> as to the Petition.</note> divers Gentlemen in great diſtreſs met together in Colonel <hi>Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Chamber at the time of the Treaty of the <hi>Scots</hi> King with the Commiſſioners at <hi>Breda,</hi> and among other things it was agreed to draw a Petition to the King, which was drawn in Colonel <hi>Druries</hi> Chamber, expreſſing their neceſſities, That the people of the Town might be Relieved, and that the Petitioners might not be left to periſh; That going to deliver it, they met with Secretary <hi>Long</hi> by the way, who told them that it was to no purpoſe, For that there was no moneys come in: afterwards the Petitioners had notice the King was to depart from <hi>Breda,</hi> Whereupon they met together again, and went into the further end of the Gallery to draw a ſhort Petition, to put the King in mind of his promiſe to Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> concerning the People of the Town of <hi>Breda,</hi> that they might be ſatisfied, and the Petitioners relieved, which Paper he the ſaid <hi>Briſco</hi> delivered to the <hi>Scots</hi> King, who threw it on a Table; And doing ſo, they ſtood all amazed, being likely to be left in diſtreſs, and unexpectedly came in the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> whereupon he the ſaid <hi>Briſco,</hi> having long ſerved in the country, and knowing him to be a lover of Souldiers, he ſpoke unto him, and ſaid, Sir, we are a company of poor diſtreſſed Gentlemen, likely to be left here in miſery (he ſaid, <hi>Well)</hi> and the next morning the King went away, without giving any relief unto the Petitioners;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119465:20"/> the Court demanded of <hi>Briſco</hi> whether there were no ſuch matter in it as <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells;</hi> He anſwered, that he Read it, and was ſure there was no ſuch thing in it, the whole ſcope of it being to relieve their neceſſities, which was the occaſion of that Petition; being demanded again by the Court, if <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells</hi> were not in the Petition; he anſwered, no, not any ſuch words at all, nor ſo much as any mention of the Parliament.</p>
               <p>Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> was in the next place produced, who teſtified, <note place="margin">Colonel <hi>Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt <hi>Faulconer,</hi> as to the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> That being at <hi>Breda,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Bardſey,</hi> Major <hi>Faulconer,</hi> Major <hi>Hall,</hi> Captain <hi>Kitchingman,</hi> and divers others came to his Lodging, and told him that they were in a condition of ſtarving, and deſired him that he would aſſiſt them to draw a Petition to the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> to relieve their neceſſities, or elſe they muſt periſh; that the ſaid <hi>Drury</hi> being in their condition, conſented unto it, and in his chamber, in his ſons paper Book the Petition was drawn, Major <hi>Faulconer</hi> writ it with his <hi>own hand,</hi> which ſaith <hi>Drury,</hi> I have here to ſhew, and ſo preſented the Original under <hi>Faulconers</hi> hand unto the Court, in which Petition (ſaid <hi>Drury)</hi> we deſired ſome relief from his Majeſty, ſhewing how we had ſerved the former King, and in what neceſſities we were in; That they were adviſed to deliver it to Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> For that they were told that the King had not a Piſtoll to relieve himſelf, and it would be a vain thing ſaid <hi>Long</hi> to deliver it; that they followed Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> and ſolicited him daily for three weeks together, and ſtill he put them off; And the day before the King went from <hi>Breda,</hi> they drew a ſhort Petition to mind the King of his promiſe to Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> and to deſire that the Inhabitants of <hi>Breda</hi> that had relieved them, might not be undone, that <hi>Briſco</hi> was deputed with him to deliver it, and he accordingly delivered it to the King, that the King laid it down upon the Table; In ſteps the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> then Captain <hi>Briſco,</hi> having trailed a Pike under the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> went to him, and told him there were many Gentlemen ready to ſtarve, and deſired him to ſpeak a favorable word to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> to which the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> anſwered, <hi>Well,</hi> as <hi>Briſco</hi> then told him: the next morning the King of <hi>Scots</hi> went away, and ſo nothing at all was done for the Petitioners; That Original Petition which <hi>Drury</hi> produced unto the Court, of <hi>Faulconers</hi> own hand writing, and in the preſence of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> was publikely Read in Court, and was as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119465:20"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>May it pleaſe your Majeſty;</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THe great ſenſe we have alwayes had of your Majeſties preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">The firſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, written with <hi>Faulco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> own hand, and produced in Court.</note> 
                        <hi>hath been the prime cauſe of our long ſilence; But now our neceſsities are grown ſo great and inſupportable, that we are inforced either to Petition or periſh: Moſt humbly deſiring your Majeſty, to take into your Princely conſideration, Their extremities who have been ever ready to proſtrate their lives in your Majeſties Royall Father his ſervice: Nor no leſs willing and ready to proſecute the ſame in what your Majeſty ſhall command: Moſt humbly petitioning your Royall Order, that ſome courſe may be taken for our preſent ſuſiſtance, that our future endevors may not be buried in that unavoydable calamity, which our loyalty hath reduced us unto.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>And we ſhall cordially pray for your Majeſty.</closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Court demanding of Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> if the ſaid Petition was <hi>Faulconers</hi> own hand writing, he ſaid yea, and looking back upon <hi>Faulconer,</hi> ſaid, he cannot deny it,: I did dictate it unto him, and <hi>Faulconer</hi> did write it in my Chamber: and that is the very O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal that was ſo drawn, and being fair written, was afterwards delivered to Secretary <hi>Long:</hi> the other that was delivered, was <hi>a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial,</hi> to put the King in mind of his promiſe when money came in; and <hi>Drury</hi> further ſaid, that when he was examined by Mr. <hi>Biſhop,</hi> he did give in his Examination, the contents of the firſt and latter Petition, and ſaid, he did expreſs himſelf at that time of his Examination by Mr. <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to the ſame effect which he had now done in Court: being asked by the Court, if the words <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells</hi> were in that firſt Petition, the ſaid <hi>Drury</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconers</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to have <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells</hi> inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that <hi>Faulconer</hi> moved to have <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells</hi> inſerted into that Petition ſo drawn by himſelf, but was anſwered by the Petitioners, that they were Souldiers of fortune, it was uncivil language, and ſo they would not give way unto it; being demanded by the Court who was deputed to deliver the laſt Petition, he ſaid, Captain <hi>Briſco</hi> was one, in regard he had many wounds at <hi>Canon-Froom,</hi> that the King might commiſerate his caſe the more, and that he the ſaid <hi>Drury</hi> was alſo deputed with <hi>Briſco</hi> to deliver the ſame, becauſe he was known to the Queen of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and ſome other perſons of quality, and <hi>Faulconer</hi> was not at all deputed: Being asked if the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was preſent at the delivery of the firſt Petition: He anſwered no, the Petition was delivered three weeks before: But the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was preſent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119465:21"/> when the laſt Petition was delivered, to mind the King of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; the ſaid <hi>Drury</hi> further informed the Court, that afterwards <hi>Faulconer</hi> being diſcontented that he got no moneys, ſaid, as he was going into the Town, <hi>This is a horrid thing, that we ſhould</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſwears he will into <hi>England</hi> and do miſchief.</note> 
                  <hi>be in this caſe, to follow</hi> a thing <hi>they call a</hi> King, (God dam me) <hi>I will go into</hi> England, <hi>and do all the miſchief I can.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Proofs as to the Credit of</hi> Faulconer.</head>
               <p>IN the next place the Counſel for the Commonwealth did apply <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge's</hi> Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt <hi>Faulconer.</hi>
                  </note> themſelves to offer proof as to the credit of <hi>Faulconer;</hi> Mr. <hi>Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge</hi> of <hi>Clements Inn,</hi> Attorney at the Common Law, being ſworn, did teſtifie to this purpoſe; That being in his chamber at <hi>Clements Inn,</hi> about this time 12 Moneth, <hi>Faulconer</hi> came to him, asked how ſome of his Countreymen neer <hi>Petersfield</hi> did? that he asked <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner</hi> where he had been of ſo long a time? Who anſwered, he had been in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> had ſeen ſome Lords ſit in Counſel for the King, that he had been ſworn againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> which would bring a great deal of advantage to the State, that he had moneys for the doing of it, and ſaid that he had received al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready 80. li. (it was that ſumme here mentioned (ſaid Mr. <hi>Woolridge)</hi> to the beſt of his remembrance) but <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſaid, he did expect <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconers</hi> confeſſion, that he had received 80. li. for what he had done in the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> buſines.</note> a greater reward; that the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> hath been as wicked a man as any in <hi>England;</hi> that he ſpent his Eſtate and left the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, did wicked acts while he was there; that being at <hi>Petersfield,</hi> he drunk an health to the Devil in the middle of the Street, of which information being given, we ſent to the Juſtice of the Peace in the Town, and had him bound over to the Seſſions for doing of it, but ſaid, he did not ſee him drink the Health to the Devil.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Jackſon</hi> of <hi>Petersfield</hi> being produced, teſtified, about <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconer</hi> drinks a health to the <hi>Devil</hi> upon his knees.</note> five years ago <hi>Faulconer</hi> was Ranting and Drinking of Healths, that he did drink a health to the Devil, and ſaid this, <hi>I have ſpent my Brothers Eſtate, and my own, I will never want money, for whilſt there is any in the Nation, I will get it one way or other, and I will do ſomething of Infamy to be talked of, that the name of</hi> Faulconer <hi>ſhall never dye:</hi> being asked in what manner he did drink the health, he anſwered, in the ſtreet, down upon his knees, that he was preſent, and thouſands can witneſs it, that he was had before a Juſtice of Peace for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Greham</hi> being ſworn, did teſtifie, that in <hi>May</hi> 1647. after <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconers</hi> attempt to Bugger a man. <hi>Faulconers</hi> Oaths.</note> the Siege at <hi>Exceſter,</hi> it was his fortune to fall into the company of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> and as he was with him in the Cellar, he was ſwearing <hi>Dam him, Blood</hi> and <hi>Wounds,</hi> takes a two &amp; twenty-ſhilling piece of Gold, puts it into his hand, and ſaid, <hi>God dam him, Blood</hi> and <hi>Wounds,</hi> he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119465:21"/> would <hi>bugger his ſoul to Hell,</hi> and theſe words he uſed frequently to Man, Woman and Childe, <hi>bugger, bugger, bugger;</hi> and correct him for it, he would ſay, <hi>Dam him, blood</hi> and <hi>wounds,</hi> he would do it; being asked by the Court, if <hi>Faulconer</hi> did any thing upon him, he anſwered, no; <hi>He was able to deal with as good Man as he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> hath often heard <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſwear, <hi>dam him</hi> and <hi>ſink</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconer</hi> a <hi>Dammee</hi> blade. <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſaid <hi>Chriſt</hi> was a <hi>Baſtard.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>him,</hi> and ſuch wicked expreſſions.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> did teſtifie, that he heard <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſay our <hi>Saviour Chriſt was a Baſtard,</hi> and a <hi>Carpenters ſon,</hi> and <hi>carried a basket of Tools after his Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Dyer</hi> being produced, did declare that <hi>Faulconer</hi> confeſſed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconer</hi> procures one to perſonate another man.</note> to him, that he had Ten pound of a man, by procuring one to perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Captain <hi>Biſhop;</hi> it was thus, (as <hi>Faulconer</hi> told him) that a Citizen, as he remembred <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſaid, did deſire <hi>Faulconer</hi> to get Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> to do a buſineſs for him, which Citizen did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe him twenty pound, ten in hand, and ten afterwards; whereupon <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſaid he got one to perſonate Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and to go along with him to the Citizen; which man ſo perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> promiſed the Citizen upon the account of Major <hi>Faulconers</hi> good ſervices for the publick, to afford him his beſt aſſiſtance in the effecting of what was deſired in his Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which Story <hi>Faulconer</hi> himſelf told; And <hi>Faulconer</hi> further ſaid, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconers</hi> intent to murder Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </note> that Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> had uſed him ill, in keeping him ſo low in money, that he had it one time in his thoughts, as Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> came from the Committee-Chamber, through the Guard-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, down the Stairs, to have cut his throat; being asked by the Court, what moneys <hi>Faulconer</hi> had of Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> he anſwered, he paid to <hi>Faulconer</hi> with his own hands, by Captain <hi>Biſhops</hi> directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <note place="margin">Fifty pound paid to <hi>Faulconer</hi> by Captain <hi>Biſhops</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. <hi>Faulconer</hi> counterfeits another mans hand, to get money of Captain <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </note> twenty pound at one time, and about thirty pound more at other times, in ſeveral Portions; that <hi>Faulconer</hi> confeſſed to him he had twenty pound afterwards; being demanded what it was for he gave that money, he ſaid, I will not ſpeak to that, I cannot ſpeak to that.</p>
               <p>Capt. <hi>Ballard</hi> being produced, did teſtifie, that about three or four years ago, he came to <hi>Faulconers</hi> Lodging, and ſaw him write a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his chamber, and that he writ it as if it had come from Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Burgeſs</hi> from <hi>Jerſey,</hi> and ſet <hi>Burgeſs</hi> his name to it, and <hi>Faulco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> would have had him the ſaid <hi>Ballard</hi> to carry this Letter to one Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> that belonged to the Council of State; and to ſay he had the Letter from one of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and get ſome money of <hi>Biſhop</hi> for that Intelligence mentioned in the Letter, of which the ſaid <hi>Ballard</hi> was to have half, but he the ſaid <hi>Ballard</hi> refuſed to go with the ſame, knowing it to be unjuſt.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> a Juſtice of Peace of the County of <hi>Middleſex</hi> did <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconer</hi> committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> for ſuſpition of Felony.</note> teſtifie to the Court, that this <hi>Faulconer</hi> was brought before him upon ſuſpition of Felony, and committed, which <hi>Mittimus</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in Court; that afterwards the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Rolls</hi> did
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119465:22"/> ſend for him out of New Priſon to Newgate; that <hi>Faulconer</hi> hath <note place="margin">A reputed high-way man. <hi>Faulconer</hi> committed to <hi>Ailesbury</hi> Gaol, for ſuſpition of Felony, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery and murder.</note> a common name for a Robber upon the high way.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Goodman,</hi> Gaoler of <hi>Ailesbury</hi> did teſtifie unto the Court, that the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> the 20th of <hi>March</hi> 1648. was committed to <hi>Ailes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> Gaol by Sir <hi>Thomas Sanders,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bulſtrode</hi> and two other Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Peace, upon ſuſpition of Felony, Robbery and Murthers, and tendered a Certificate thereof in Writing unto the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Defence made on the behalf of</hi> Faulconer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe evidence being given on the behalf of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, Mr. <hi>Windham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Latch,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lechmore,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Haggat,</hi> of Counſel for <hi>Faulconer,</hi> did offer ſomething to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Court before they did produce their witneſſes <hi>viz.</hi> That although it concerns every man that perjury ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; <note place="margin">Matter offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coners</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel before they deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Proof.</note> For every mans Life, Liberty, Fortune and Eſtate depends upon an Oath, and in theſe times it is ſomewhat dangerous if they ſhould be forſworn; So on the otherſide, if <hi>Faulconer</hi> be not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn, it is but juſt he ſhould be acquit: That the Counſel for the Commonwealth have endeavoured to prove that there was a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, but that there was no ſuch words in the Petition as are ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, and have endeavoured to impeach the credit of <hi>Faulconer:</hi> That they have produced a Copy of <hi>Faulconers</hi> Oath, which ought not to be admitted, becauſe it is but a Tranſcript of a Tranſcript, a Copy of a Copy, brought from <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall</hi> to the Council of State, and from the Council of State to the Parliament, and there the Copy is entred in the Journal Book: And the witneſſes that have been produced, do not ſwear poſitively to the Oath as it is in writing, and one particle may turn the whole ſenſe of an Oath: And though theſe words <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells</hi> were in it, Yet how it is applied, and how the ſenſe of it fals, it cannot be judged, but by the Original writing it ſelf, and it concerns the Counſel for the Keepers to produce it: How it ſhould come into <hi>Faulconers</hi> hands, there is no account given, but by one <hi>Knight,</hi> Who ſaith <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſhewed him a thing, which <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſaid was his [Original] depoſition againſt the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> but the credit of <hi>Knights</hi> Teſtimony is left to the Jury: It is ſworn that that Copy produced in Court was examined, but Mr <hi>Winſlow</hi> doth not poſitively ſay it was examined by the Original, when in their cuſtody.</p>
               <p>That as to the witneſſes produced againſt the credit of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> they did hope to counterpoiſe his life to be, as of a man that might be credited: That in the Petition delivered at <hi>Breda,</hi> there is ſomething
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119465:22"/> of thoſe words, though there be not <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells,</hi> which was but a nominal thing; yet the proſtrating of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to proſecute the cauſe, is deſired may be obſerved, though the actual words be not there, yet the ſenſe doth bear it; that the caſe is ſomewhat hard with <hi>Faulconer,</hi> who was imployed at the Court at <hi>Breda</hi> as an Emiſſary, as a Spye: And at his return in giving an account of his obſervations at <hi>Breda,</hi> let ſomething fall concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> without any deſign in him, and that what <hi>Faulconer</hi> delivered in his depoſition was with qualifications, as he did believe to his beſt remembrance, and the like.</p>
               <p>Hereupon Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> was produced on the behalf of <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Captain <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> dicourſe, not applicable to the perjury in queſtion.</note> as a witneſs, whoſe diſcourſe was long, and conſiſted of three parts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It took notice how the Council of State ſent for him from his habitation at <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> to be imployed in matters of great truſt, and afterwards what truſt was repoſed in him and Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> in order to the ſafety of the Nation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By way of Argument on behalf of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> he did declare what ſervices <hi>Faulconer</hi> had done for the Commonwealth, and that <hi>Faulconer</hi> was one by whom this Commonwealth ſate ſafe at this hour, and by whom he enjoyed his life: And what an ill requitall this was to be thus proceeded againſt.</p>
               <p>The third part of his diſcourſe was, to declare what particular deſigns the State formerly had in hand, and what deſigns the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had againſt the State: and what ſervice he did to countermine the enemy in their deſigns: The laſt of the three being not (as was conceived) ſo adviſedly ſpoken in publike, and which would be more unfit to be in print: Shall therefore here be paſt over in ſilence, as alſo what Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſaid at large concerning the two firſt particulars, In reſpect they are no proofs pertinently to be applied, as to the perjury in queſtion.</p>
               <p>A brief account only ſhall be therefore given what Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> properly ſpoke as a witneſs.</p>
               <p>As a <hi>witneſs,</hi> Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſaid, he had never ſeen <hi>Faulconer</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The ſubſtance of Captain <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</note> in drink or misbehave himſelf, but ever obſerved him as a ſober man, that he did draw <hi>Faulconers</hi> information [which <hi>Faulconer</hi> did deliver as the <hi>ſubſtance]</hi> and that he muſt ſay, that the words <hi>[or to that effect]</hi> ſhould have been put in, and that it was his fault they were not in, and he could not tell but that they were in; That the Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall</hi> were deſired to come to <hi>White-Hall</hi> to Adminiſter an Oath to the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leaſt danger ſhould befall the witneſſes if they were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Horſnel</hi> was formerly an Agent for the Prince, and was to receive orders from <hi>Tom Cook</hi> in the Tower, and was ordered to be tried by the high Court of Juſtice: That Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> was
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119465:23"/> a Papiſt in Arms, and being brought before him to be examined, ſtill had the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> in his mouth, before he was asked a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p>The like of <hi>Briſco.</hi> He ſaid, that before <hi>Drury</hi> and <hi>Briſco</hi> came from beyond Seas, his Agent gave him notice of their coming, And thereupon he laid wait for them, and caught them; that <hi>Drury</hi> ſaid, when he was examined, that he had not a penny of money, that he did not commit him to Priſon, but took his Paroll, and in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration gave him two ſhillings ſix pence for his Supper; He ſaid further, that <hi>Drury</hi> did contradict himſelf in what he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly informed the Council of State, and to that end produced in Court the Copy of <hi>Druries</hi> Information, which being read in Court, agreed with the Teſtimony which <hi>Drury</hi> then gave to the Jury.</p>
               <q>By way of Digreſſion obſerve, <hi>That</hi> Druries <hi>and</hi> Briſcoes <note place="margin">Obſerve.</note> 
                  <hi>Informations which Captain</hi> Biſhop <hi>had taken, above twelve moneths ſince, and which tended to clear the Lord</hi> Craven, <hi>he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed till this hour that he produced the ſame in Court, and never tranſmitted thoſe two mens Examinations to the Parliament; Though before the Bill of Sale did paſs, he did tranſmit</hi> Bardſeys <hi>and</hi> Kitchingmans <hi>Re-examination taken by himſelf, and which he apprehended made againſt the Lord</hi> Craven.</q>
               <p>Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> further ſaid, That whereas it was objected that <hi>Faulconer</hi> had money: he anſwered, that it is great reaſon he ſhould have monies, for there was a real effect of the ſafety of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth by his ſervices; that notwithſtanding any thing hath been ſworn againſt <hi>Faulconer,</hi> he believes what he ſwore was truth.</p>
               <p>Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſpeaking again of <hi>Faulconers</hi> Depoſition, that the words <hi>[or to that effect]</hi> ſhould have been added: the Court asked him whether <hi>Faulconer</hi> gave any directions to expreſs theſe words in his Examination: to which Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> made anſwer, that the Depoſition he made, was the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of things, and he put it in words, and that <hi>[or to that effect]</hi> if they were not in, ſhould have been in. The Court again asked him if <hi>Faulconer</hi> did direct him to put in theſe words <hi>[or to that effect]</hi> he replyed again, he did deliver the whole, <hi>as the effect of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> being further asked by the Court, if he were preſent when the Commiſſioners gave the Oath, and took what <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſaid in way of information, he anſwered, <hi>That he prepared it before the Commiſsioners were ſent for,</hi> and then they had only the adminiſtring the Oath; and ſaid again, <hi>I prepared the information which he made oath of;</hi> hereupon Mr. <hi>Winſlow</hi> deſired leave to inform the Court, that when he and the reſt of the Commiſſioners came to <hi>White-hall</hi> to adminiſter this Oath, being ſent for to that end,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119465:23"/> the information was <hi>Ready prepared</hi> by Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and having no Regiſter with them, they made uſe of Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> being well skilled in the uſe of his Pen, to write over the Depoſition, for though he had prepared the Depoſition, the Commiſſioners did ſee occaſion to alter much of it, and it was writ over again, and then <hi>Read</hi> to <hi>Faulconer,</hi> and <hi>atteſted by him,</hi> and ſubſcribed unto by the hands of all the Commiſſioners then preſent; and the Oath which we gave him was this, <hi>Whether the Depoſition thus drawn, and that which he was examined unto, was the Truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth;</hi> Mr. <hi>Barners</hi> atteſted the like: then Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſat down.</p>
               <p>After this Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Joyce</hi> was produced, who likewiſe <note place="margin">Leiutenant Colonel <hi>Joyce</hi> his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</note> ſpake of very great deſigns, and of matters of State, and what diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries were made by <hi>Faulconer,</hi> which being not pertinent to the Perjury, ſhall be here omitted; But as a Witneſs he ſaid, That <hi>Horſnel</hi> was formerly an agent for the Prince.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Faulconer</hi> was a <hi>Hampſhire-</hi>man, a Gentleman well bred that he was an Enemy to himſelf in ſpending his Eſtate, that he was always faithful to the Parliament, that he believes <hi>Faulconer</hi> hath cuft ſome of the Witneſſes produced againſt him for their Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy, and that nothing could be expected to come from them to the credit of <hi>Faulconer:</hi> That <hi>Faulconer</hi> was ſent over by him as a <hi>Spie</hi> into <hi>Holland</hi> upon an account of faithfulneſs.</p>
               <p>Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Bardſey</hi> was produced in the next place on <note place="margin">Leiutenant Colonel <hi>Bard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money.</note> the behalf of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> who teſtifyed, that he put his hand to the Petition at <hi>Breda,</hi> that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was deſired to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it to the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> ſaid he was no Courtier, but a Servant to the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> that it was fitter for the Princeſs Royal to deliver it then himſelf, and ſo returned the Petition again; that the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> told the Petitioners the King would do for them what he was able; but about 4 a clock in the morning he went away, and they had no other anſwer: that the Contents of it was to put the King in minde of his promiſe, that ſome money might be delivered to the Petitioners for diſcharge of their quarters at <hi>Breda;</hi> being asked by the Court, if there were any expreſſions in it, as <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells,</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered no: being asked, if to that Petition which <hi>Faulconer</hi> drew, he would have had <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells</hi> added; he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, yea, <hi>Faulconer</hi> did move to have thoſe words in, but was refuſed; that he the ſaid <hi>Bardſey</hi> read over that Petition, and ſet his hand to it, and was at the penning of it, and <hi>Faulconer</hi> wrote it.</p>
               <p>Captain <hi>Kitchingman</hi> being produced, did teſtifie, that a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Captain <hi>Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chingman</hi> his Teſtimony.</note> was drawn at <hi>Breda,</hi> and ſigned by him, <hi>Faulconer,</hi> and others, to be preſented to the King of <hi>Scots;</hi> that it was in purſuance of gaining moneys to diſcharge their Quarters, and to enable them to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119465:24"/> ſerve the King, but knows not by whom it was delivered; that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary <hi>Long</hi> was to iſſue out moneys unto them, but they never had any; and in order to the gaining of that money, there was another Petition drawn, but by whom delivered, he knew not; only he ſaw a Paper in the Queen of <hi>Bohemia's</hi> hand, which was told him was the Petition, and after a quarter of an hours diſcourſe with the King, Shee delivered it to the King, but they never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any money upon that neither: That he did not read the laſt Petition at all, nor heard it read; that it was the firſt Petition which he ſigned.</p>
               <p>Colonel <hi>Dove</hi> was produced in Court on the behalf of <hi>Faulco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Colonel <hi>Dove</hi> his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</note> who ſaid, he knew nothing of his Birth, he only knew his Father and Mother, that they lived in good Faſhion and Credit, but how this <hi>Faulconer</hi> hath been brought up, and where he hath inhabited for theſe ten or twelve years, he knew not, and that this was as much as he could ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Michel,</hi> an Ale-houſe-keeper was then produced, who ſaid he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Michel</hi> an Ale-houſe-keeper his Teſtimony.</note> knew nothing of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> but that he was a very honeſt man, <hi>Faulconer</hi> having lain in his houſe a year and three quarters; that he knows nothing to the contrary, but that he was a good Scholler, an honeſt man, and brought up at the Univerſity.</p>
               <p>Captain <hi>Mowbrey</hi> being produced as a Witneſs, did teſtifie, that <note place="margin">Captain <hi>Mowbrey</hi> his Teſtimony.</note> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1649. in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> he met accidentally with Captain <hi>Briſco,</hi> who ſaid to him and others, Gentlemen, I ſee you are in a ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, I will ſet you in a way to get money; here are Dutch Men taking up Men to go to Plantations, and you ſhall have twelve Stivers a piece a day, but I will warrant you, I will force them to leave you behinde, and accordingly they received twelve Stivers a day, and <hi>Briſco</hi> would have had them on Ship-board, but one <hi>Church</hi> an Engliſh Man bid them take heed what they did; for he ſerved ſome Engliſh men ſo before, clap them under decks, and received ſo many ſix Dollers a piece for them, and ſo left them; That he hath known <hi>Faulconer</hi> five years, and he hath behaved himſelf civilly for ought he ever ſaw.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Corey</hi> did teſtifie ſomething to this purpoſe, in reference to <hi>Briſcoes</hi> ſending men to Plantations; who ſaid further, he had no <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Corey</hi> his Teſtimony.</note> more to ſay againſt <hi>Briſco,</hi> but that he was a man would drink, and ſometimes ſwear as well as other men that are accuſtomed to it, that he knows nothing to the contrary, but that he came to <hi>Breda</hi> to wait for imployment: in the mean time whilſt he was there, he did as other men did, ſtrive to ſeek for Relief.</p>
               <p>After the Court had with much patience heard Captain <hi>Biſhop</hi> and the reſt of the Witneſſes on the behalf of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> The Counſel for <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſumm'd up the Evidence, and left it to the Jury, with ſome further obſervations, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119465:24"/>
               <p> That though the words <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells</hi> were not <note place="margin">Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made by the Counſel on the behalf of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> after the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence given.</note> in the Petition, yet there were words of <hi>tender of Service,</hi> as the King ſhould command, and to proſecute his cauſe, which was the ſubſtance of the thing informed by <hi>Faulconer;</hi> That Captain <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and Lieuteuant Colonel <hi>Joyce,</hi> who have teſtified of <hi>Faulconers</hi> ſervices, were witneſſes to be preferred before any witneſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced againſt <hi>Faulconer;</hi> That the endeavour is not onely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict this man, but by conviction and diſabling of his credit, to undermine that which hath been acted by the Parliament upon his Teſtimony, and other concurrent Teſtimonies, not only in paſſing Votes, but in paſſing an Act of Parliament to ſell an Eſtate.</p>
               <p>That there was nothing objected againſt the credit of this wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo long as there was any other ſtone to turn, though there were other endevors uſed in Parliament to prevent the Sale of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Eſtate, ſo that when all other Refuges failed, then they make uſe of this Indictment of Perjury, and ſo hope to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine the Act of Parliament; Though <hi>Faulconer</hi> might have ſome extravigance, yet you ſee what his part was to Act, to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble</hi> that he was not what he was, and it may be when he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>God-dammees,</hi> and ſuch kind of men, it was his part to ſeem to be what moſt conduced to his end, <hi>[Like themſelves,]</hi> For a man as he was imployed muſt twine himſelf into all ſhapes, and though not drink a health, yet ſometimes <hi>hold a candle to the Devil;</hi> That they acknowledge the charge in part, and would lay it in <hi>words,</hi> not in <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and therefore not ſtrictly in the Letter true.</p>
               <p>That it was proved that the firſt Petition was to ſerve the King, as they formerly had ſerved his Father, and they ſerved his Father againſt the Parliament: ſo their offer muſt needs be, to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to ſerve the King againſt the Parliament.</p>
               <p>That it is a ſad caſe that this man for ſo many ſervices performed by him for the Commonwealth, and ſetlements grounded upon his information, muſt be blaſted here by an <hi>artificial Indictment</hi> a great while after.</p>
               <p>And if he ſhall after all this be convicted of perjury, it will be a diſcouragement for all men to undertake the like imployment for the future.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, The Counſel for <hi>Faulconer</hi> did offer; That if there be a miſtake in what he hath ſworn, yet it appears not to be mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly or corruptly done, and that therefore the Jury ought to find for <hi>Faulconer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119465:25"/>
               <head>The Reply by the Counſel on the behalf of the Commonwealth againſt <hi>Faulconer,</hi> was to this purpoſe following.</head>
               <p>GEntlemen of the Jury, You have heard the defence that <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Reply againſt <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner.</hi>
                  </note> hath made; We have charged him, that he did take the Oath that was ſet down in the Indictment; They ſay, Firſt, We have not proved it; Secondly, That he did not take it, but did take it in effect; And thirdly, If he did, it was not maliciouſly, nor corruptly; But <hi>not one</hi> of them hath ſaid it is not <hi>falſe,</hi> no not one of their own Counſel; The evidence that hath been given for the moſt part, hath been to magnifie the ſervice of this man that is now in queſtion before you: We ſhall admit his ſervices to be true, but this we ſhall be bold to ſay, that a man that is imployed beyond Sea, and gives good return of his ſervice in ſome kind, That that will not give him Licenſe to make a falſe Accuſation in another kind; and it is no Argument to ſay, that becauſe this man was a <hi>Spie</hi> beyond the Sea, and did good ſervice as a <hi>Spie,</hi> that therefore he did not give a falſe Information: In this he muſt not take a liberty to ruine any man by a <hi>falſe Oath:</hi> His ſervice muſt not excuſe him, if what he hath ſaid be falſe.</p>
               <p>And for what Mr. <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſaid concerning his Oath; for Mr. <hi>Biſhop</hi> tells you, it is his fault if the words <hi>[Or to that effect]</hi> were not put down; if it were not, whoſe fault was it? It was mended by thoſe whoſe Judgements and Conſciences induced them to it: The Information he took was done by the Judgement of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, and not by the direction of him that was a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> a <hi>Scribe</hi> to write, and not a Judge to dictate and correct: You have here two men of unqueſtionable truth and honeſty every way (meaning Mr. <hi>Winſlow,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Barners)</hi> that ſay poſitively he did ſwear it, and God forbid that we ſhall live to that day, that any man ſhould be ruined upon a Depoſition taken by the Judgement of a <hi>Clerk,</hi> to ſuch or ſuch <hi>effect;</hi> If we ſhould come to ſuch a peece of Juſtice, that a Depoſition to ſuch and ſuch effect, and that taken by a <hi>Clerk,</hi> ſhould come to caſt a man, it is beyond an Oath of <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For it is the Judges that muſt ſay what is the effect of an Oath, and not the Clerk that writes it: If a Clerk ſhall take an Oath, and he ſhall come and ſay, <hi>it is to this effect,</hi> never ſhall any man be free from him that by Perjury will ruine another man: It is proved unto you, it was read over to <hi>Faulconer,</hi> expreſly mended in his ſight, and ſworn by him, and let the <hi>effect</hi> go with the <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that went before it.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119465:25"/>
               <p> They objected to our witneſſes, that <hi>Briſco</hi> had ſold his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions for twelve Stivers a day; that information had no other foundation then the ſaying of a <hi>Dutchman,</hi> that ſaid ſo, or of an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> in a <hi>Dutch</hi> bottom; And what was teſtified, was what was ſaid, and not what was known or ſworn; they objected that <hi>Briſco</hi> would ſwear as well as another; that takes not off his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; But what do they ſay concerning their own witneſs <hi>Bard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> whom they have produced? He hath ſworn <hi>in terminis,</hi> in effect with <hi>Drury,</hi> which you will not forget: He ſwore, that when the firſt Petition was drawing, it was moved by <hi>Faulconer</hi> that the words <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells</hi> ſhould be put in, but is was rejected by them that were there, as a thing uncivil; ſo their own witneſs concurs with <hi>Drury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Depoſition on Record at <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> which being filed there, it is proof of it ſelf, which no man may aver againſt, when it is recorded; We have ſhewed it there, traced it here, brought a Copy of it endorſed with the Lord <hi>Bradſhaws</hi> hand; ſhall it be believed that a man ſhall be confiſcated and looſe his Eſtate, and not ſo much as an Oath taken againſt him? It is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent there was an Oath, and it is hoped you will believe that which the Parliament hath Recorded, and expreſly proved by the Gentlemen of <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall</hi> here preſent, which you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve before any Imaginations can be made on the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</p>
               <p>They have endeavoured to ſay ſomething touching the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of this man, to uphold his credit; But Gentlemen of the Jury, You are to conſider of the man, what <hi>damnable blaſphemy</hi> hath come out of his mouth, you have heard it: If a man will go ſo high, as to kneel down to <hi>drink a health to the Devil,</hi> I hope there is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for that; his good ſervices muſt not plead for him to comply with <hi>God-dammees,</hi> that will not juſtifie him, he was not ſent to do any ſuch thing: But we have not reſted there; Have we not proved him a <hi>perſonator</hi> of other men, a <hi>Decoy,</hi> and things that a man ſhould be aſhamed to name: the two and twenty ſhillings peece he took out, and what baſe vilde words he ſpake, not fit to be repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? That will not be palliated by any ſervice whatſoever. And for that which Mr. <hi>Biſhop</hi> hath ſaid, nothing ſhall be ſaid againſt him, but what appears to you: that Mr <hi>Biſhop</hi> hath gone beyond a witneſs: for when he hath done his Teſtimony, <hi>acteth</hi> and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageth</hi> the buſineſs, and in that is not equal to others that do not: For his expreſſion, that <hi>Faulconer</hi> is one of them by which the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> ſits ſafe at this hour: It is God we ſit ſafe by, and not by him: I blame him not for his ſervice, but when we are upon a queſtion of truth, I ſay truth and righteouſneſs is beyond all the ſervice in the world.</p>
               <p>They ſay my Lord <hi>Craven</hi> furthered the Petition, and promiſed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119465:26"/> to ſecond it: Gentlemen, you muſt diſtinguiſh that which my Lord <hi>Craven</hi> knew, &amp; that which he knew not: There is <hi>not one witnes from beginning to ending that ever can ſpeak one word that my Lord</hi> Craven <hi>knew what the firſt Petition was:</hi> In that Petition was the expreſſion of venturing their lives, which was three weeks before the latter, which was ſingly to deſire they might have money for their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: The firſt Petition had ſome expreſſions relating to their former ſervice, and ſome expreſſions of their readineſs for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but that Petition my Lord <hi>Craven</hi> never ſaw, but was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to one <hi>Long</hi> three weeks before, and <hi>Drury</hi> did put it down in his Depoſition when he was examined by Mr. <hi>Biſhop,</hi> which agrees with that which was read in Court.</p>
               <p>But the particular time when the latter Petition or Memorial was delivered, with which the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> is charged, was the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the King went from <hi>Breda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They ſay that here is no corruption proved, and a man cannot be guilty without corruption: but certainly he that ſwears a thing that is falſe, it muſt of neceſſity be corrupt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faulconer</hi> ſwears that thirty Officers did ſubſcribe the Petition: Doth he bring any one to confirm his Teſtimony, or the leaſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of evidence to what he hath ſworn?</p>
               <p>It was further preſſed by the Counſel for the Commonwealth, that the Jury would diſtinguiſh theſe two things, between the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition framed and dictated by <hi>Drury,</hi> and writ by <hi>Faulconer;</hi> and that other Petition delivered the night before the King went from <hi>Breda;</hi> the firſt is produced, and proved to be <hi>Faulconers</hi> own hand: that Petition was three weeks before, which begs for maintenance, and proffers ſervice, the Copy of which was brought forth before any Evidence was given by them, for <hi>Drury</hi> upon his Examination before the Council of State made the ſame known, and which agrees <hi>verbatim</hi> with that read in Court; ſo the dictating of that Petition was by <hi>Drury,</hi> the writing by <hi>Faulconer,</hi> the delivery was to Secretary <hi>Long,</hi> and that was the thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they did expect an Account; but that was not the Petition to which the Teſtimony of <hi>Faulconer</hi> at all goes: that Petition of which this Oath is ſpoken, and to which it is applyed, is the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition which was drawn the Evening before the <hi>Scots</hi> King went from <hi>Breda,</hi> that is the Petition talked of in the Depoſition, that is the Petition upon which we pitch, and therefore if in that Petition there be none of theſe words, that which he hath ſworn unto is falſe: for in that Petition we ſay there was no ſuch words, as <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and Inhumane Rebells:</hi> nor ſuch words of proffer of ſervice or malignity, but a meer deſire of ſupply: and they have not offered the leaſt proof to the contrary. And Secondly, that it was not promoted by the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> for the Petition was delivered by them to the <hi>Scots</hi> King, before ſuch time as the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> came
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119465:26"/> into the room, ſo that my Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was no Promoter of the Petition; and had he been a Promoter of it, there was no ſuch thing in it as might give offence: no not the leaſt mention of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any thing that might offend; and whereas they object that this Oath was not corrupt, the very words of his expreſſion are very conſiderable, for he doth remarkably fix the words in his Depoſition, <hi>To ſight againſt the Commonwealth of</hi> England, by the name of <hi>Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells:</hi> why would he fix ſuch an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> upon it as that was? it could not be a bare miſtake: nor the words <hi>to this effect,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Biſhop</hi> would have had in, could never have ſerved the turn, for to ſay that he would fight againſt <hi>the Barbarous and Inhamane Rebells,</hi> or to that effect, there is no ſuch effect in the one Petition nor in the other: Then a ſecond thing is, that this <hi>Faulconer</hi> being, as he depoſeth, the contriver of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, it could not be a meer overſight and miſtake in him; And then when he could not have his deſire beyond Seas, to get mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, he ſaid, <hi>He would come here and do what miſchief he could.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Counſel urged further: Gentlemen of the Jury, what is become of the original Depoſition, it concerns not us to know, no more then the Original of Depoſitions taken in the Countrey: it lies upon them that are for the Oath to make it out. It cannot be preſumed that the Parliament would confiſcate a Noble Mans Eſtate, and order it to be ſold: would they enter it into the Journal Book, and make it a Record: ſhould it come and be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall</hi> (the proper Judicatory for that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) to the Council of State, and from the Council of State to the Parliament, and then not to be a true oath, or falſe Copy? that is not to be born, that a falſe Copy ſhould ſell a Gentlemans Eſtate, and that a falſe Copy ſhould be recorded to ſtand to all Eternity.</p>
               <p>After the Reply was made; every Judge in Court ſpoke what they in their Judgement thought fit, for the better direction of the Jury; whereupon the Jury withdrew, and the next day brought in their Verdict, that they found the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> guilty of the Perjury mentioned in the Indictment. The Order following was thereupon made, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="verdict">
                  <body>
                     <head>By the Court.</head>
                     <p>The Defendant was this day brought into Court, under the Cuſtody <note place="margin">Middleſex: <hi>The keepers</hi> &amp;c. <hi>againſt</hi> Faulconer.</note> of the Marſhall of this Court, upon an Indictment for Perjury, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he had formerly pleaded <hi>Not guilty;</hi> And the Jury thereupon being impannelled, and ſworn, found him guilty of the Perjury in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment mentioned: And thereupon the ſaid <hi>Faulconer</hi> is committed to the Cuſtody of the ſaid Marſhall; there to remain untill, &amp;c.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
